<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quantum Field Theory | George Johnson</title>
    <link>/category/quantum-field-theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/quantum-field-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Quantum Field Theory</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu7bc565721a69e427bf94bf1315c635aa_13529_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>/category/quantum-field-theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model V: Summary and Extensions</title>
      <link>/blog/sm5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;extensions&#34;&gt;Extensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series we have discussed the symmetries of the Standard Model in its &amp;lsquo;standard&amp;rsquo; form. Some aspects of the theory, such as the Higgs sector and the neutrino mass terms, have not been definitively established, and it is quite possible that nature behave somewhat differently from the present model. For example, electroweak symmetry could be broken by an extended sector, containing the Higgs boson alongside other scalar fields. Likewise, the neutrino masses may receive contributions (solely or partially) from Majorana terms. The current model is merely the simplest one consistent with current experimental constraints, but future experiments may demand that we extend our model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, even at present there are several theoretical and experimental motivations for such extensions. Attempts to understand why the gauge group takes the form it does, why there are three generations, and why each generation has the structure it does, lead naturally to grand unified theories, with a single simple gauge group. On the other hand, the existence of dark matter and the apparent non-existence of the QCD theta term motivate the addition of further fields to the theory. In this final part of the series we will look at some natural extensions of the Standard Model, and how they impact its symmetries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;majorana-neutrinos&#34;&gt;Majorana Neutrinos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is in fact one term we have neglected to add to the Lagrangian throughout this series, consistent with both renormalizability and the gauge symmetry of the theory. This is the Majorana mass term for the right-handed neutrinos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_m = -m \epsilon^{ab} \nu^a_R \nu^b_R + \mathrm{h.c.}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here $m$ is a matrix in flavour space. Such a term exists only for the right-handed neutrinos since they are the only fields in the theory which transform as singlets under each factor of the gauge group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Majorana mass term violates lepton number (and also breaks explicitly the $T^3_R$ subgroup of $SU(2)_R$). Thus, with the inclusion of this term the theory possesses no non-anomalous exact global symmetries ($B-L$ being the only such symmetry previously). The only exact anomalous symmetry of our new Lagrangian is baryon number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diagonalisation of the mass terms is slightly more complicated in this case, though it is straightforward to sketch the effect on the discrete symmetries. We note that $\mathcal{L}_m$ above is not invariant under neutrino rephasings, unlike the diagonalised Yukawa mass terms. Thus, after diagonalisation, the mass terms possess only a $U(1)^3$ flavour symmetry (corresponding to charged lepton rephasings), and this allows us to remove only three phases from the PMNS matrix. There are thus three $CP$-violating phases in the lepton sector in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-higgs-doublets&#34;&gt;Two Higgs Doublets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it is possible to give all fermions mass &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; break electroweak symmetry with just a single complex scalar doublet, there is an (only marginally more complicated) alternative involving two such doublets. Experimental constraints on the Higgs sector are weak, and such a scenario is consistent with current data.  Moreover, in theories such as those involving supersymmetry or axions, it is often natural or even necessary for two Higgs doublets to exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the simplest of such models, the quark Yukawa terms and Higgs potential are replaced by the Lagrangian:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\mathcal{L}_{2HD} = V(\phi_1,\phi_2) - Y_d \bar{Q}_L \phi_1 d_R - Y_u \bar{Q}_L \phi_2^c u_R + \mathrm{h.c.}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the leptons, we can freely choose to couple each Yukawa term to either of the two Higgs fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maximum possible symmetry of the potential is $U(2)_1 \times U(2)_2$, which we can write as $SU(2)_1 \times U(1)_1 \times SU(2)_2 \times U(1)_2$ up to discrete quotients. However, the couplings to $Q_L$ prevent us from performing independent $SU(2)$ rotations of the two Higgs doublets, and so in fact the maximum symmetry of our Lagrangian is $SU(2) \times U(1)_1 \times U(1)_2$. The two $U(1)$ factors (corresponding to independent rephasings of the two Higgs fields) can equally be written as the product of a &amp;lsquo;vectorial&amp;rsquo; $U(1)$ (rephasing both fields by the same amount) and an &amp;lsquo;axial&amp;rsquo; $U(1)$ (rephasing both fields by opposite amounts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quarks and leptons must be charged under these two $U(1)$ symmetries if the Yukawa terms are to be invariant. Indeed, the required charges under the vectorial symmetry are precisely the hypercharges $Y$ of the Standard Model. Under axial rephasings, which we shall denote $U(1)_X$, we can take all right-handed quarks to have charge $-1/2$ and all left-handed quarks charge zero. The exact lepton charges will depend on the binary choices made in that sector. The maximal symmetry group of our Lagrangian can hence be written $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \times U(1)_X$ &amp;mdash; that is, as the product of the electroweak symmetry group with a single new global symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most general potential invariant under this group is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{align}
V(\phi_1,\phi_2) = &amp;amp;\lambda_1 (\phi_1^\dagger \phi_1)^2 - \mu_1^2 \phi_1^\dagger \phi_1  + \lambda_2 (\phi_2^\dagger \phi_2)^2 - \mu_2^2 \phi_2^\dagger \phi_2 \\ &amp;amp;+\lambda_3 (\phi_1^\dagger \phi_1)(\phi_2^\dagger \phi_2) +  \lambda_4 (\phi_1^\dagger \phi_2)(\phi_2^\dagger \phi_1) \ .
\end{align}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the potential is such that both fields acquire a vacuum expectation value, then in general there will be no unbroken symmetry. Thus, we must restrict the form of the potential further to reproduce the correct pattern of symmetry breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; An unbroken generator $T$ satisfies $T \phi_1^0 = T \phi_2^0  = 0$, where $\phi_{1,2}^0$ are the vacuum expectation values of the Higgs fields. Working with the convention that $\phi_1^0 = (0,v)$, show that all five of the above symmetries are broken unless $\phi_1^0$ and $\phi_2^0$ are parallel or perpendicular. Show that in either case there is only one unbroken symmetry, and that it is (respectively) $T^3 + Y$ or $T^3 + X$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;axions&#34;&gt;Axions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We mentioned in Part IV that in principle the Standard Model should contain a QCD theta term, but that no effects of this term have yet been discovered. This is not for lack of trying, however. Indeed, current experiments constrain the constant $\theta_{QCD}$ to be less than about $10^{-10}$. Why this parameter should be so unnaturally small is known as the &lt;strong&gt;strong CP problem&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also claimed that the QCD theta term would be unphysical if there existed a symmetry (such as the chiral rotation of a single quark flavour) which was respected by the Lagrangian but which suffered a QCD anomaly. With general Yukawa matrices (as in reality), no such symmetry exists. We may attempt to rephase $u_R$ only, for example, but the structure of the Yukawa terms requires that we also rephase the Higgs and, in turn, the other right-handed fermions, in order to maintain invariance. Such a symmetry is necessarily some combination of $B-L$ and hypercharge $Y$, and is non-anomalous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Peccei-Quinn solution to the strong CP problem invokes a second Higgs doublet to bypass the above obstruction. Indeed, the symmetry $U(1)_X$ of the previous section is both respected by the Lagrangian (by construction) and suffers a QCD anomaly (by virtue of acting equally on only right-handed quarks). In this context we call $U(1)_X$ the Peccei-Quinn symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the exercise in the previous section illustrates, $U(1)_{PQ}$ must be spontaneously broken by any potential which does not break $Q = T^3 + Y$. Hence, our theory must contain a Nambu-Goldstone boson associated with the Peccei-Quinn symmetry. This boson is known as the &lt;strong&gt;axion&lt;/strong&gt;. The axion is not exactly massless on account of the anomaly, but is nevertheless light. The existence of a new light scalar particle would appear to have observable consequences, and indeed the axion we have described here has been ruled out experimentally. Nevertheless, the Peccei-Quinn theory forms the basis for more complicated axion models which are compatible with current observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the summary tables from the previous parts of the series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QED ($\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QCD and QED&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T_R^1$ and $T_R^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T^1$ and $T^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B+L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electroweak&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B-L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QCD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Electroweak&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QED&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$P$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T$ or $CP$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{CKM} = \theta_{PMNS} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model IV: Discrete Symmetries</title>
      <link>/blog/sm4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three discrete &amp;lsquo;spacetime&amp;rsquo; symmetries of importance in any quantum field theory. These are &lt;strong&gt;charge conjugation&lt;/strong&gt; $C$, &lt;strong&gt;parity&lt;/strong&gt; $P$, and &lt;strong&gt;time-reversal&lt;/strong&gt; $T$. The CPT theorem states that any Lorentz-invariant local quantum field theory will be invariant under the product operation $CPT$. We will hence consider $CP$ and $T$ to be equivalent symmetry operations. None of these symmetries is anomalous nor spontaneously broken in the Standard Model. We will hence discuss in turn the sectors of the theory in which they are respected or violated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-kinetic-terms&#34;&gt;The Kinetic Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without coupling the fermions to the $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$ gauge fields, we find that the kinetic terms for the gauge fields, the fermions, and the Higgs (that is, all terms except the Yukawa terms) are invariant under all three discrete symmetries. However, since the left- and right-handed fermions couple differently under $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, these coupling terms violate both $C$ and $P$. They nevertheless preserve the combined symmetry $CP$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since $CP$ is the only discrete symmetry respected by the kinetic terms, we will focus on this symmetry alone in the next two sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-yukawa-terms-----quarks&#34;&gt;The Yukawa Terms &amp;mdash; Quarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We established in Part III that the Yukawa matrices $Y_u, Y_d$ could be taken without loss of generality to be Hermitian and positive semi-definite, and were uniquely determined by this requirement. We will assume this convention henceforth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The action of $CP$ on the Yukawa terms is a symmetry if $Y_u$ and $Y_d$ are real matrices. Generically they will not be. However, in unitarity gauge we can independently rotate (vectorially) the up-type and down-type quarks to diagonalise the Yukawa matrices: take
$u_{L,R} \to U_u u_{L,R}$ and $d_{L,R} \to U_d d_{L,R}$ so that
$$ U_u^\dagger Y_u U_u = D_u \quad \mathrm{and} \quad U_d^\dagger Y_d U_d = D_d  \ . $$
The eigenvalues of these matrices are the (real and non-negative) masses of the quarks. After such a rotation, the Yukawa terms become real and hence $CP$-symmetric, and additionally enjoy a $U(1)^6$ flavour symmetry (at the least).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This field redefinition disturbs only one other term in the Lagrangian, which is the coupling of the weak charged current to the charged $W^\pm$ bosons. In particular:
$$ \bar{u}_L \gamma^\mu d_L \to \bar{u}_L U _u^\dagger U_d \gamma^\mu d_L  \ . $$
The matrix $V = U_u^\dagger U_d$ is known as the CKM matrix. A general unitary matrix has $n_g^2$ real parameters, of which $n_g(n_g+1)/2$ are complex phases. We can use the aforementioned freedom to rephase our quarks without disturbing the Yukawa terms to reduce the number of parameters in this matrix: $V \to U^\dagger V$ or $V \to V U$ where $U = \mathrm{diag}(e^{i \alpha}, e^{i \beta}, e^{i \gamma})$. Note that the $U(1)_B$ subgroup of $U(1)^6$ has trivial action on $V$. We can thus reduce the nine parameters in $V$ down to four (not three), of which one must be a complex phase, known as the CKM phase. All four parameterers are non-zero in the Standard Model. The CKM phase violates $CP$. The other three real parameters characterise the size of the mixing between quark flavours. Since these are all non-zero, there are no global flavour symmetries in the quark sector besides the flavour-blind $U(1)_B$, as we alluded to in Part III.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We note that if $g = 0$, there is no CP violation, even if our Lagrangian originally had complex Yukawa matrices (this illustrates that whilst no discrete symmetries may be initially apparent, an appropriate field redefinition can reveal one). As such, though we began this section considering the symmetries of the Yukawa terms, we say that CP violation from the CKM phase is a &lt;em&gt;weak interaction effect&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; show that with $n_g$ generations, the CKM matrix contains $(n_g-1)(n_g-2)/2$ complex phases. Conclude that three generations is the minimum required for weak CP violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-yukawa-terms-----leptons&#34;&gt;The Yukawa Terms &amp;mdash; Leptons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above analysis applies identically to the lepton sector. The phase in the mixing matrix is known as the PMNS phase in this case, rather than the CKM phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We note that if we take $Y_\nu = 0$, so that the neutrinos are massless, then we can diagonalise the Yukawa matrices without disturbing the weak charged current (simply choose $U_\nu = U_e$). In this case $CP$ will be exact, and in addition there will be an exact $U(1)^3$ flavour symmetry, corresponding to conservation of lepton number in each generation. For a time it was thought that the neutrinos were exactly massless, and that these were indeed exact symmetries. It is now known this is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More generally, we see that we can arrange for $V = I$ so long as the Yukawa matrices can be simultaneously diagonalised. For Hermitian matrices (and diagonalisable matrices more generally) this is equivalent to $[Y_e, Y_\nu] = 0$. Thus if the Yukawa matrices commute, both $CP$ and individual lepton number will be symmetries of the theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, $CP$ alone will be a symmetry under weaker requirements. Any degeneracy of eigenvalue in one of the two Yukawa matrices bestows the Yukawa terms with an additional $SU(2)$ symmetry (alongside $U(1)^6$). This is sufficient to remove the single complex phase for $n_g = 3$. Thus, with three generations, there will be no weak CP violation if there is a single pair of degenerate charged leptons &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; neutrinos (and a single pair of degenerate up-type quarks &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; down-type quarks). For $n_g = 3$, a degenerate eigenvalue implies $\det[Y_e, Y_\nu] = 0$. Thus we can claim that $\theta_{PMNS}$ is physical if $\det[Y_e, Y_\nu] \neq 0$ (and likewise for the quark sector).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phases $\theta_{CKM}$ and $\theta_{PMNS}$ are the two sources of &lt;strong&gt;weak CP violation&lt;/strong&gt; in the Standard Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-theta-terms&#34;&gt;The Theta Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an additional class of term one can add to the Standard Model Lagrangian that we mentioned in Part I but have ignored since then. These are the theta terms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\theta =  \frac{\theta g^2}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are precisely the terms that appear on the right-hand sides of anomalous current conservation equations, as we have seen in Parts II and III. They violate both $P$ and $T$ (and so $CP$), but not $C$. In general such terms can be removed by a field redefinition corresponding to an anomalous symmetry. However, since we have made various such transformations in order to simplify the Yukawa terms, any attempts to remove the theta terms thus will appear to reintroduce symmetry-violating phases into other parts of the Lagrangian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, having exhausted chiral rotations of the right-handed fermions to make the Yukawa matrices Hermitian, and having exhausted vectorial rotations of the fermions to diagonalise the Yukawa matrices and subsequently simplify the CKM and PMNS matrices, the only transformations which remain for us to exploit are those which are genuine symmetries of the Lagrangian. However, to introduce or remove any theta term, such a symmetry must be anomalous. There is only one such symmetry, $B + L$, and hence in general only one theta term can be removed. Since the divergence of the corresponding current contains only $SU(2)_L$ and $U(1)_Y$ gauge fields, the QCD theta term cannot be removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that if one of the quarks is massless, then $U(1)_R$ (for that quark flavour) is a symmetry of the Lagrangian. Argue that in this case, we can remove the QCD theta term. We can thus claim that $\theta_{QCD}$ is physical if $\det(Y_u Y_d) \neq 0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It transpires, however, that the $U(1)_Y$ theta term is always unphysical. It can be seen that the theta terms are in fact total derivatives, and so their effects are non-perturbative. Whether they have any effect at all depends on whether there exist field configurations (that are pure gauge at infinity) such that this surface term is non-zero &amp;mdash; such configurations are known as &lt;strong&gt;instantons&lt;/strong&gt;. In four spacetime dimensions instantons exist only if the third homotopy group of the gauge group is non-trivial. Since $\pi_3(U(1)) = \{0\}$ and $\pi_3(SU(n)) = \mathbb{Z}$ for $n \geq 2$, there exist only $SU(3)_C$ and $SU(2)_L$ instantons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absence of $U(1)_Y$ instantons compels us to perform a $U(1)_{B+L}$ field redefinition that removes the $SU(2)_L$ theta term, leaving the QCD theta term as the only one with physical consequences. The phase $\theta_{QCD}$ is the sole source of &lt;strong&gt;strong CP violation&lt;/strong&gt; in the Standard Model (we reiterate that it also violates $P$). No effects of this term have yet been discovered, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since neither $C$, $P$, nor $T$ is anomalous nor spontaneously broken by the vacuum, we here classify these symmetries according to whether they are respected in the following three cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QCD: we set $g = g&#39; = 0$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electroweak: we set $g_s = 0$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QED: we set $g_s = 0$ and ignore the Higgs and massive gauge bosons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QCD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Electroweak&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QED&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$P$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T$ or $CP$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{CKM} = \theta_{PMNS} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model III: The Higgs Sector</title>
      <link>/blog/sm3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this part of the series we will discuss the global symmetries of the full Standard Model Lagrangian. We will first consider the terms involving just the Higgs, then those coupling the Higgs to the fermions, and then those coupling the Higgs to the gauge bosons. Lastly, we will consider symmetries acting only on the fermion fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-higgs-potential&#34;&gt;The Higgs Potential&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Higgs Lagrangian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\phi = |D_\mu \phi|^2 + \mu^2 \phi^\dagger \phi - \lambda( \phi^\dagger \phi)^2  $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is by construction invariant under the gauge symmetry $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, where we take $Y = 1/2$ by convention and let $\phi$ transform in the fundamental of $SU(2)_L$. However, the Higgs potential is in fact invariant under a larger symmetry group. This is easiest to see by writing $\phi$ in terms of its real and imaginary parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \phi = \begin{pmatrix} \phi_2 + i \phi_1 \\ \phi_0 - i \phi_3 \end{pmatrix}  \ ,$$
so that
$$ \phi^\dagger \phi = \sum_i \phi_i^2  \ .$$
Then there is an obvious $O(4)$ symmetry. Ignoring discrete quotients, we have $O(4) = SU(2) \times SU(2)$. To see this decomposition explicitly in the case of the Higgs field, we can construct the matrix
$$ \Phi = \begin{pmatrix} \phi_0 + i \phi_3 &amp;amp;  \phi_2 + i \phi_1 \\ - \phi_2 + i \phi_1 &amp;amp; \phi_0 - i \phi_3 \end{pmatrix} = \phi_0 I + i \sum_i \phi_i \sigma_i \ . $$
Note that $\Phi = |\phi| U$ where $U \in SU(2)$. Then we have
$$ \phi^\dagger \phi = \frac{1}{2}\mathrm{tr}(\Phi^\dagger \Phi) \ ,$$
which is invariant under the transformation
$$ \Phi \to U_L \Phi U_R^\dagger \ ,$$
where $U_{L,R} \in SU(2)$  (one can check that if $U_{L,R}$ are allowed to lie in $U(2)$ instead, they do not generally preserve the form of $\Phi$ as a real multiple of a special unitary matrix). The reader can check that the left action on $\Phi$ corresponds precisely to the action of $SU(2)_L$ on the original field $\phi$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Higgs acquires a vacuum expectation value, so that $\Phi \propto I$, this symmetry group is spontaneously broken down to the diagonal subgroup, with $U_L = U_R$. This symmetry is known as &lt;strong&gt;custodial symmetry&lt;/strong&gt;, $SU(2)_V$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exactness-----the-yukawa-terms&#34;&gt;Exactness &amp;mdash; The Yukawa Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider first a single generation of quarks. The Yukawa terms are
$$ \mathcal{L}_y = -y_d \bar{Q}_L \phi d_R - y_u \epsilon^{ab}\bar{Q}_{La} \phi^*_b u_R  +\mathrm{h.c.}  $$
By construction this Lagrangian is invariant under $SU(2)_L$, but does not appear to be invariant under $SU(2)_R$ (defined to act on doublets of right-handed fermions analogously to $SU(2)_L$). However, in the case that $y_u = y_d = y$, one can write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_y = -y \bar{Q}_L \Phi Q_R + \mathrm{h.c.} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is evidently invariant under $SU(2)_R$. With multiple generations, the complex numbers $y_u,y_d$ become complex matrices, which we will denote $Y_u,Y_d$. As above, $SU(2)_R$ will be a symmetry if $Y_u = Y_d$. However, since we can freely rotate the right-handed down-type quarks amongst themselves without disturbing any other term in the Lagrangian (and likewise for the right-handed up-type quarks), this requirement is a little too strict. In fact, $SU(2)_R$ will be a symmetry provided $Y_u$ and $Y_d$ are related by right-multiplication by a unitary matrix. In the case of a single generation, this just requires that $|y_u| = |y_d|$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that any square matrix $Y$ can be written as the product $HU$ where $H$ is Hermitian and positive semi-definite and $U$ is unitary. This is known as polar decomposition, and defines $H$ uniquely. We can hence use the freedom to rotate the right-handed fermions to ensure, without loss of generality, that the Yukawa matrices are Hermitian and positive semi-definite. With this convention, $SU(2)_R$ is a symmetry if and only if $Y_u = Y_d$ and $Y_e = Y_\nu$. This condition does not hold in reality, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since $SU(2)_L$ is always a symmetry of the Yukawa terms, the very same condition is necessary and sufficient for custodial $SU(2)_V$ to be exact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that the above condition can be expressed in a convention-independent manner as
$$ Y_u^\dagger Y_u = Y_d^\dagger Y_d \quad \mathrm{and} \quad  Y_e^\dagger Y_e = Y_\nu^\dagger Y_\nu \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exactness-----kinetic-terms-and-hypercharge&#34;&gt;Exactness &amp;mdash; Kinetic Terms and Hypercharge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ is truly the full symmetry group of the Higgs potential, and the first factor is the familiar gauged $SU(2)_L$ group, then hypercharge must be a subgroup of the second factor. Indeed, it is not too difficult to show that hypercharge acts on the Higgs $\Phi$ as the $T^3_R$ generator of $SU(2)_R$. However, hypercharge does not act on the quarks and leptons in this way. In fact, the generator of hypercharge can be written
$$ Y = T^3_R + B/2 - L/2 \ ,$$
where $B$ and $L$ are the generators of baryon number and lepton number respectively. Since only some subgroup of $SU(2)_R$ is gauged, and not the entirety of it, $SU(2)_R$ is not an exact symmetry of the theory (unless we set $g&#39; = 0$). To see this explicitly from the Lagrangian, we can consider the Higgs kinetic terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without gauge couplings, the kinetic terms of the Higgs are invariant under the full $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ symmetry group, just as the potential is. When we gauge the $SU(2)_L$ subgroup, the additional terms in the Lagrangian (coupling the Higgs to the gauge fields) are only invariant as a result of the global transformation properties of the gauge fields:
$$ W_\mu \to U W_\mu U^{-1} \ .$$
Thus, the problematic terms are those that involve the hypercharge gauge field $B_\mu$ (proportional to the matrix $T_R^3$), which does not transform under the action of the generators $T_R^1$ and $T_R^2$, nor commute with them:
$$ \begin{align} \mathrm{tr}(B^\mu \Phi^\dagger \Phi  B_\mu) \to \ &amp;amp;\mathrm{tr}(B^\mu (1 - i\alpha_iT_R^i)  \Phi^\dagger \Phi (1 + i\alpha_j T_R^j) B_\mu) \\&lt;br&gt;
\neq \ &amp;amp;\mathrm{tr}(B^\mu \Phi^\dagger \Phi  B_\mu) \ . \end{align}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that the kinetic terms for the fermions also break $SU(2)_R$ explicitly when $g&#39; \neq 0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise: both the Yukawa terms and the coupling to the hypercharge gauge boson explicitly break the full $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ symmetry, but they leave intact both $SU(2)_L$ and the $T^3_R$ generator of $SU(2)_R$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fermion-symmetries-and-anomalies&#34;&gt;Fermion Symmetries and Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having considered the Higgs sector in some detail, we should ask whether there are any additional symmetries that act only on the fermions. If the Yukawa matrices are general (as they are in reality), the only possible symmetries are $U(1)$ rephasings of fermion flavours and chiralities. In fact, as we will justify more fully in Part IV, the only such symmetries are the vectorial and flavour-blind symmetries $U(1)_B$ and $U(1)_L$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though exact, both of these symmetries suffer an electroweak anomaly:
$$ \partial_\mu J_B^\mu = \partial_\mu J_L^\mu = \frac{n_g}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma}\left( g^2 W^a_{\mu \nu} W^a_{\rho \sigma} - {g&#39;}^2 B_{\mu \nu} B_{\rho \sigma}  \right) \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the divergences of the baryon number current and lepton number current are identical, we see that the combination of global symmetries $B - L$ is non-anomalous, and indeed is the only such exact global continuous symmetry in the Standard Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T_R^1$ and $T_R^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T^1$ and $T^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B+L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electroweak&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B-L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model II: The Quark Sector</title>
      <link>/blog/sm2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low energies, the Standard Model has unbroken gauge group $SU(3)_C \times U(1)_Q$. The heavy Higgs and massive gauge bosons can be ignored, leaving a theory of massless gauge bosons and several flavours of Dirac fermion. We will discuss the continuous global symmetries of this theory, focusing on the quark sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;flavour-symmetries&#34;&gt;Flavour Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With $n_f$ flavours of quark, the largest possible global symmetry group consists of independent unitary rotations of the left-handed quarks and the right-handed quarks, that is, $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R $. Such symmetries are sometimes called &lt;strong&gt;flavour symmetries&lt;/strong&gt;. Ignoring discrete symmetry quotients, this can be written
$$ SU(n_f)_L \times SU(n_f)_R \times U(1)_L \times U(1)_R  \ .$$
It is sometimes useful to rewrite left- and right-handed rotations in terms of rotations of both chiralities by the same amount and by opposite amounts. Such symmetries are called &lt;strong&gt;vector symmetries&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;axial symmetries&lt;/strong&gt; respectively. Thus we are tempted to write the above symmetry group as
$$ SU(n_f)_V \times SU(n_f)_A \times U(1)_V \times U(1)_A  \ .$$
In fact there is a small subtlety here. It is not the case that axial special unitary transformations form a group (they are not closed under composition). More precisely, we should think of $SU(n_f)_A$ as the coset $SU(n_f)_L \times SU(n_f)_R  / SU(n_f)_V$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exact-symmetries&#34;&gt;Exact Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a symmetry is exact when all the quarks are massless. If the quarks are not massless but all have the same mass, the vector symmetry is exact but none of the axial symmetries are. In the case that all the quark masses are different and non-zero, as in reality, the exact symmetry group is $U(1)_V^{n_f}$, corresponding to number conservation of each quark flavour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; show that if there are $n_0$ massless quarks and $n_i$ quarks of mass $m_i &amp;gt; 0$, then the exact symmetry group is
$$  U(n_0)_R \times U(n_0)_L \times \prod_i U(n_i)_V  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Standard Model, the lightest three quarks (the up, down, and strange) have sufficiently small masses that for $n_f = 3$ we can consider $U(n_f) \times U(n_f)$ to be a good approximate symmetry. It is an even better approximate symmetry for $n_f = 2$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spontaneous-symmetry-breaking&#34;&gt;Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All axial symmetries are broken by the vacuum due to the non-zero VEV of the quark bilinears $\bar{q}q$. Note that the broken gauge symmetry $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, acting on quarks, is in fact a subgroup of $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R$, provided we take $n_f = 6$. And indeed, spontaneous breaking of the axial symmetries translates into spontaneous breaking of the gauge symmetry down to $U(1)_Q$. One might wonder, therefore, whether the chiral condensate alone could be responsible for this pattern of symmetry breaking. However, this will naturally give the gauge bosons masses of order the QCD scale (around $100\ \mathrm{MeV})$ rather than the observed scale of $100\ \mathrm{GeV}$. Furthermore, the Higgs serves a second purpose in the Standard Model (in addition to breaking electroweak symmetry), which is to give masses to the quarks and leptons. Without the Higgs, the gauge symmetry can only be exact if all the quarks and leptons are massless, which is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;anomalies&#34;&gt;Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as being inexact and spontaneously broken by the vacuum, the axial symmetries are also anomalous. In particular, axial $U(1)_A$ suffers both a QCD anomaly and a QED anomaly. There is also one generator of axial $SU(n_f)_A$ which suffers a QED anomaly &amp;mdash; for $n_f = 3$ this is $\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$. The aforementioned QCD anomaly is the supposed explanation for the lack of a fourth ($n_f = 2$) or ninth ($n_f = 3$) light meson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might suspect that the QED anomaly suffered by $SU(n_f)_A$ would also raise the masses of some of the other light mesons. This is a rather complicated story which we will briefly discuss in Part IV. For the present moment we note that if we neglect electric charge ($e = 0$), the only anomalous symmetry is axial $U(1)_A$:
$$ \partial_\mu J_5^\mu = -\frac{n_f g_s^2}{32 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma}F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lepton-sector&#34;&gt;The Lepton Sector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle a similar study is warranted of the global continuous symmetries of the lepton sector. However, this is vastly more simple. Firstly, without the strong dynamics of QCD, there is no chiral condensate, so no spontaneous symmetry breaking. Secondly, the lepton masses are sufficiently different that no flavour symmetry can fairly be called approximate. We note, however, that to the extent that any $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R$ flavour symmetry &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be considered approximate, the axial symmetries would suffer a QED anomaly as in the quark case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; As we stated in Part I, a generator $T$ of $SU(n_f)_A$ suffers a QED anomaly if $\mathrm{tr}(TQ^2) \neq 0$, where $Q$ is the generator of electric charge. Show that in general there is one such anomalous generator, but that if we consider a flavour symmetry amongst only the charged leptons, or only the neutrinos, then there is no QED anomaly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QED ($\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QCD and QED&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Note that the two diagonal generators of $SU(3)_V$ are exact symmetries. One of these can be identified with electric charge $Q$. Together with $U(1)_V$ they form the $U(1)^3_V$ symmetry group corresponding to conservation of each quark flavour.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model I: Overview</title>
      <link>/blog/sm1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standard Model is a complicated quantum field theory. Understanding it in detail takes time, but understanding the symmetries of the theory provides a framework with which to understand these details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Symmetries can be classified along many lines. They can be continuous or discrete, global or local, approximate or exact, anomalous, spontaneously broken, and so on. In this series, we will endeavour to discuss each and every symmetry of the Standard Model, and classify them according to each of the categories above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Part I, we will give a schematic overview of the structure of the Standard Model and its gauge symmetries. In Parts II and III we will consider global continuous symmetries, first from the perspective of the low-energy theory, and then from the perspective of the high-energy theory. In Part IV we will consider the discrete symmetries $C$, $P$, and $T$, and in Part V we will collect these results together and discuss how they are affected by some extensions to the theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gauge-symmetries&#34;&gt;Gauge Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting point for the construction of the Standard Model is the gauge group&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \ , $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the first factor represents the colour symmetry of &lt;strong&gt;quantum chromodynamics (QCD)&lt;/strong&gt;, and the second two factors (known as weak isospin and hypercharge) represent the symmetry of the &lt;strong&gt;electroweak&lt;/strong&gt; interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-field-content&#34;&gt;The Field Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standard Model contains gauge bosons corresponding to each of the gauge groups described above, along with $n_g = 3$ generations of Weyl fermions in the following representations, as well as a single scalar field, the Higgs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$SU(2)_L$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$U(1)_Y$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Q_L$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 1/6$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$u_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 2/3$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$d_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1/3$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$L_L$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1/2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$e_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$\nu_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$\phi$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 1/2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lagrangian&#34;&gt;The Lagrangian&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most general renormalizable Lagrangian with the above gauge symmetry and field content is the Standard Model. We can group the terms in the Lagrangian into four classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the gauge fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the fermions, including coupling to the gauge fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the Higgs and Higgs self-interactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yukawa couplings between the fermions and the Higgs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schematically, this Lagrangian is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \begin{align} \mathcal{L} = &amp;amp;-\frac{1}{4} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^{a\mu \nu} \\ &amp;amp;+ \bar{\psi} i  \gamma^\mu D_\mu \psi \\ &amp;amp;+ |D_\mu \phi|^2 - V(\phi) \\ &amp;amp;- Y_d \bar{Q}_L \phi d_R - Y_u \bar{Q}_{L} \phi^c u_R + \mathrm{h.c.} \\ &amp;amp;- Y_e \bar{L}_L \phi e_R - Y_\nu \bar{L}_{L} \phi^c \nu_R + \mathrm{h.c.} \end{align} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an additional class of term one can add to the Lagrangian whose effects are more subtle. These are the theta terms, one for each factor of the gauge group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\theta =  \frac{\theta g^2}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will ignore these terms until Part IV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exact-symmetries&#34;&gt;Exact Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lagrangian above has many approximate global symmetries which we will discuss in due course. The extent to which these symmetries are approximate is dictated by the various parameters of the theory. For general choices of these parameters (and in reality) the Standard Model has only two exact global continuous symmetries. These are &lt;strong&gt;baryon number&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;lepton number&lt;/strong&gt;. They are not enforced upon the theory &amp;mdash; rather, it is simply not possible to write down renormalizable terms respecting the overall gauge symmetry which violate baryon or lepton number. We sometimes say such symmetries are &lt;strong&gt;accidental&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spontaneous-symmetry-breaking&#34;&gt;Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A symmetry is spontaneously broken if it is respected by the Lagrangian but not by the vacuum of the theory. Spontaneous symmetry breaking is typically caused by fields acquiring a non-zero expectation value in the vacuum. In the Standard Model, there are two sources of spontaneous symmetry breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Higgs field $\phi$ acquires a non-zero VEV. This breaks the gauge symmetry thus:
$$ SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \to SU(3)_C \times U(1)_Q \ .$$
It also breaks some approximate global symmetries. This is known as &lt;strong&gt;electroweak symmetry breaking&lt;/strong&gt;. The unbroken $U(1)_Q$ symmetry is the symmetry of &lt;strong&gt;quantum electrodynamics (QED)&lt;/strong&gt;. We will discuss this further in Part III.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a lower energy scale, the quark bilinears $\bar{q}q$ acquire a non-zero VEV (equal in magnitude for each flavour). This breaks no further gauge symmetries, but does break some approximate global symmetries. This is known as &lt;strong&gt;chiral symmetry breaking&lt;/strong&gt;. We will discuss this further in Part II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;anomalies&#34;&gt;Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A symmetry is anomalous if it is respected by the Lagrangian but not by the path integral measure. For a symmetry $H$ with generators $t^a$ and a gauge symmetry $G$ with generators $T^a$, we say that $H$ suffers a $G$-anomaly if the &lt;strong&gt;anomaly coefficient&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathrm{tr}(\gamma^5 t^a \{T^b, T^c\}) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is non-zero. In principle it is possible for anomalies to arise from diagrams with three different currents, but this cannot happen in the Standard Model since such diagrams always involve exactly one generator of $SU(2)_L$ or $SU(3)_C$, which is traceless. It is a somewhat magical feature of the Standard Model, which one should check from the table of field representations above, that no gauge symmetry $H$ suffers a $G$-anomaly for any gauge symmetry $G$. Indeed, this is necessary for the theory to be consistent. Nevertheless, there are several global symmetries $H$ which suffer $G$-anomalies, as we shall see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
