<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quantum Field Theory | George Johnson</title>
    <link>/category/quantum-field-theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/quantum-field-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Quantum Field Theory</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu7bc565721a69e427bf94bf1315c635aa_13529_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>/category/quantum-field-theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model III: The Higgs Sector</title>
      <link>/blog/sm3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will here discuss the global symmetries of the full Standard Model Lagrangian. We will first consider the terms involving just the Higgs, then those coupling the Higgs to the fermions, and then those coupling the Higgs to the gauge bosons. Lastly, we will consider symmetries acting only on the fermion fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-higgs-potential&#34;&gt;The Higgs Potential&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Higgs Lagrangian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\phi = |D_\mu \phi|^2 + \mu^2 \phi^\dagger \phi - \lambda( \phi^\dagger \phi)^2  $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is by construction invariant under the gauge symmetry $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, where we take $Y = 1/2$ by convention and let $\phi$ transform in the fundamental of $SU(2)_L$. However, the Higgs potential is in fact invariant under a larger symmetry group. This is easiest to see by writing $\phi$ in terms of its real and imaginary parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \phi = \begin{pmatrix} \phi_2 + i \phi_1 \\ \phi_0 - i \phi_3 \end{pmatrix}  \ ,$$
so that
$$ \phi^\dagger \phi = \sum_i \phi_i^2  \ .$$
Then there is an obvious $O(4)$ symmetry. Ignoring discrete quotients, we have $O(4) = SU(2) \times SU(2)$. To see this decomposition explicitly in the case of the Higgs field, we can construct the matrix
$$ \Phi = \begin{pmatrix} \phi_0 + i \phi_3 &amp;amp;  \phi_2 + i \phi_1 \\ - \phi_2 + i \phi_1 &amp;amp; \phi_0 - i \phi_3 \end{pmatrix} = \phi_0 I + i \sum_i \phi_i \sigma_i \ . $$
Note that $\Phi = |\phi| U$ where $U \in SU(2)$. Then we have
$$ \phi^\dagger \phi = \frac{1}{2}\mathrm{tr}(\Phi^\dagger \Phi) \ ,$$
which is invariant under the transformation
$$ \Phi \to U_L \Phi U_R^\dagger \ ,$$
where $U_{L,R} \in SU(2)$  (one can check that if $U_{L,R}$ are allowed to lie in $U(2)$ instead, they do not generally preserve the form of $\Phi$ as a real multiple of a special unitary matrix). The reader can check that the left action on $\Phi$ corresponds precisely to the action of $SU(2)_L$ on the original field $\phi$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Higgs acquires a vacuum expectation value, so that $\Phi \propto I$, this symmetry group is spontaneously broken down to the diagonal subgroup, with $U_L = U_R$. This symmetry is known as &lt;strong&gt;custodial symmetry&lt;/strong&gt;, $SU(2)_V$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exactness-----the-yukawa-terms&#34;&gt;Exactness &amp;mdash; The Yukawa Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider first a single generation of quarks. The Yukawa terms are
$$ \mathcal{L}_y = -y_d \bar{Q}_L \phi d_R - y_u \epsilon^{ab}\bar{Q}_{La} \phi^*_b u_R  +\mathrm{h.c.}  $$
By construction this Lagrangian is invariant under $SU(2)_L$, but does not appear to be invariant under $SU(2)_R$ (defined to act on doublets of right-handed fermions analogously to $SU(2)_L$). However, in the case that $y_u = y_d = y$, one can write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_y = -y \bar{Q}_L \Phi Q_R + \mathrm{h.c.} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is evidently invariant under $SU(2)_R$. With multiple generations, the complex numbers $y_u,y_d$ become complex matrices, which we will denote $Y_u,Y_d$. As above, $SU(2)_R$ will be a symmetry if $Y_u = Y_d$. However, since we can freely rotate the right-handed down-type quarks amongst themselves without disturbing any other term in the Lagrangian (and likewise for the right-handed up-type quarks), this requirement is a little too strict. In fact, $SU(2)_R$ will be a symmetry provided $Y_u$ and $Y_d$ are related by right-multiplication by a unitary matrix. In the case of a single generation, this just requires that $|y_u| = |y_d|$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that any square matrix $Y$ can be written as the product $HU$ where $H$ is Hermitian and positive semi-definite and $U$ is unitary. This is known as polar decomposition, and defines $H$ uniquely. We can hence use the freedom to rotate the right-handed fermions to ensure, without loss of generality, that the Yukawa matrices are Hermitian and positive semi-definite. With this convention, $SU(2)_R$ is a symmetry iff $Y_u = Y_d$ and $Y_e = Y_\nu$. This condition does not hold in reality, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since $SU(2)_L$ is always a symmetry of the Yukawa terms, the very same condition is necessary and sufficient for custodial $SU(2)_V$ to be exact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that the above condition can be expressed in a convention-independent manner as
$$ Y_u^\dagger Y_u = Y_d^\dagger Y_d \quad \mathrm{and} \quad  Y_e^\dagger Y_e = Y_\nu^\dagger Y_\nu \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exactness-----kinetic-terms-and-hypercharge&#34;&gt;Exactness &amp;mdash; Kinetic Terms and Hypercharge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ is truly the full symmetry group of the Higgs potential, and the first factor is the familiar gauged $SU(2)_L$ group, then hypercharge must be a subgroup of the second factor. Indeed, it is not too difficult to show that hypercharge acts on the Higgs $\Phi$ as the $T^3_R$ generator of $SU(2)_R$. However, hypercharge does not act on the quarks and leptons in this way. In fact, the generator of hypercharge can be written
$$ Y = T^3_R + B/2 - L/2 \ ,$$
where $B$ and $L$ are the generators of baryon number and lepton number respectively. Since only some subgroup of $SU(2)_R$ is gauged, and not the entirety of it, $SU(2)_R$ is not an exact symmetry of the theory (unless we set $g&#39; = 0$). To see this explicitly from the Lagrangian, we can consider the Higgs kinetic terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without gauge couplings, the kinetic terms of the Higgs are invariant under the full $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ symmetry group, just as the potential is. When we gauge the $SU(2)_L$ subgroup, the additional terms in the Lagrangian (coupling the Higgs to the gauge fields) are only invariant as a result of the global transformation properties of the gauge fields:
$$ W_\mu \to U W_\mu U^{-1} \ .$$
Thus, the problematic terms are those that involve the hypercharge gauge field $B_\mu$ (proportional to the matrix $T_R^3$), which does not transform under the action of the generators $T_R^1$ or $T_R^2$, nor commute with them:
$$ \mathrm{tr}(B^\mu \Phi^\dagger \Phi  B_\mu) \to \mathrm{tr}(B^\mu (1 - i\alpha_iT_R^i)  \Phi^\dagger \Phi (1 + i\alpha_j T_R^j) B_\mu)  \neq \mathrm{tr}(B^\mu \Phi^\dagger \Phi  B_\mu) \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that the kinetic terms for the fermions also break $SU(2)_R$ explicitly when $g&#39; \neq 0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise: both the Yukawa terms and the coupling to the hypercharge gauge boson explicitly break the full $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ symmetry, but they leave intact both $SU(2)_L$ and the $T^3_R$ generator of $SU(2)_R$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fermion-symmetries-and-anomalies&#34;&gt;Fermion Symmetries and Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having considered the Higgs sector in some detail, we should ask whether there are any additional symmetries that act only on the fermions. If the Yukawa matrices are general (as they are in reality), the only possible symmetries are $U(1)$ rephasings of fermion flavours and chiralities. In fact, as we will justify more fully in Part IV, the only such exact symmetries are the vectorial and flavour-blind symmetries $U(1)_B$ and $U(1)_L$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though exact, both of these symmetries suffer an electroweak anomaly:
$$ \partial_\mu J_B^\mu = \partial_\mu J_L^\mu = \frac{n_g}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma}\left( g^2 W^a_{\mu \nu} W^a_{\rho \sigma} - {g&#39;}^2 B_{\mu \nu} B_{\rho \sigma}  \right) \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the divergences of the baryon number current and lepton number current are identical, we see that the combination of global symmetries $B - L$ is non-anomalous, and indeed is the only such exact global continuous symmetry in the Standard Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T_R^1$ and $T_R^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T^1$ and $T^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B+L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electroweak&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B-L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model II: The Quark Sector</title>
      <link>/blog/sm2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low energies, the Standard Model has unbroken gauge group $SU(3)_C \times U(1)_Q$. The heavy Higgs and massive gauge bosons can be ignored, leaving a theory of massless gauge bosons and several flavours of Dirac fermion. We will discuss the continuous global symmetries of this theory, focusing on the quark sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;flavour-symmetries&#34;&gt;Flavour Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With $n_f$ flavours of quark, the largest possible global symmetry group consists of independent unitary rotations of the left-handed quarks and the right-handed quarks, that is, $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R $. Such symmetries are sometimes called &lt;strong&gt;flavour symmetries&lt;/strong&gt;. Ignoring discrete symmetry quotients, this can be written
$$ SU(n_f)_L \times SU(n_f)_R \times U(1)_L \times U(1)_R  \ .$$
It is sometimes useful to rewrite left- and right-handed rotations in terms of rotations of both chiralities by the same amount and by opposite amounts. Such symmetries are called &lt;strong&gt;vector symmetries&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;axial symmetries&lt;/strong&gt; respectively. Thus we are tempted to write the above symmetry group as
$$ SU(n_f)_V \times SU(n_f)_A \times U(1)_V \times U(1)_A  \ .$$
In fact there is a small subtlety here. It is not the case that axial special unitary transformations form a group (they are not closed under composition). More precisely, we should think of $SU(n_f)_A$ as the coset $SU(n_f)_L \times SU(n_f)_R  / SU(n_f)_V$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exact-symmetries&#34;&gt;Exact Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a symmetry is exact when all the quarks are massless. If the quarks are not massless but all have the same mass, the vector symmetry is exact but none of the axial symmetries are. In the case that all the quark masses are different and non-zero, as in reality, the exact symmetry group is $U(1)_V^{n_f}$, corresponding to number conservation of each quark flavour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; show that if there are $n_0$ massless quarks and $n_i$ quarks of mass $m_i &amp;gt; 0$, then the exact symmetry group is
$$  U(n_0)_R \times U(n_0)_L \times \prod_i U(n_i)_V  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Standard Model, the lightest three quarks (the up, down, and strange) have sufficiently small masses that for $n_f = 3$ we can consider $U(n_f) \times U(n_f)$ to be a good approximate symmetry. It is an even better approximate symmetry for $n_f = 2$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spontaneous-symmetry-breaking&#34;&gt;Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All axial symmetries are broken by the vacuum due to the non-zero VEV of the quark bilinears $\bar{q}q$. Note that the broken gauge symmetry $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, acting on quarks, is in fact a subgroup of $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R$, provided we take $n_f = 6$. And indeed, spontaneous breaking of the axial symmetries translates into spontaneous breaking of the gauge symmetry down to $U(1)_Q$. One might wonder, therefore, whether the chiral condensate alone could be responsible for this pattern of symmetry breaking. However, this will naturally give the gauge bosons masses of order the QCD scale (around $100\ \mathrm{MeV})$ rather than the observed scale of $100\ \mathrm{GeV}$. Furthermore, the Higgs serves a second purpose in the Standard Model (in addition to breaking electroweak symmetry), which is to give masses to the quarks and leptons. Without the Higgs, the gauge symmetry can only be exact if all the quarks and leptons are massless, which is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;anomalies&#34;&gt;Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as being inexact and spontaneously broken by the vacuum, the axial symmetries are also anomalous. In particular, axial $U(1)_A$ suffers both a QCD anomaly and a QED anomaly. There is also one generator of axial $SU(n_f)_A$ which suffers a QED anomaly &amp;mdash; for $n_f = 3$ this is $\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$. The aforementioned QCD anomaly is the supposed explanation for the lack of a fourth ($n_f = 2$) or ninth ($n_f = 3$) light meson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might suspect that the QED anomaly suffered by $SU(n_f)_A$ would also raise the masses of some of the other light mesons. This is a rather complicated story which we will briefly discuss in Part IV. For the present moment we note that if we neglect electric charge ($e = 0$), the only anomalous symmetry is axial $U(1)_A$:
$$ \partial_\mu J_5^\mu = -\frac{n_f g_s^2}{32 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma}F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lepton-sector&#34;&gt;The Lepton Sector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle a similar study is warranted of the global continuous symmetries of the lepton sector. However, this is vastly more simple. Firstly, without the strong dynamics of QCD, there is no chiral condensate, so no spontaneous symmetry breaking. Secondly, the lepton masses are sufficiently different that no flavour symmetry can fairly be called approximate. We note, however, that to the extent that any $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R$ flavour symmetry &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be considered approximate, the axial symmetries would suffer a QED anomaly as in the quark case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; As we stated in Part I, a generator $T$ of $SU(n_f)_A$ suffers a QED anomaly if $\mathrm{tr}(TQ^2) \neq 0$, where $Q$ is the generator of electric charge. Show that in general there is one such anomalous generator, but that if we consider a flavour symmetry amongst only the charged leptons, or only the neutrinos, then there is no QED anomaly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QED ($\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QCD and QED&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Note that the two diagonal generators of $SU(3)_V$ are exact symmetries. One of these can be identified with electric charge $Q$. Together with $U(1)_V$ they form the $U(1)^3_V$ symmetry group corresponding to conservation of each quark flavour.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model I: Overview</title>
      <link>/blog/sm1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standard Model is a complicated quantum field theory. Understanding it in detail takes time, but understanding the symmetries of the theory provides a framework with which to understand these details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Symmetries can be classified along many lines. They can be continuous or discrete, global or local, approximate or exact, anomalous, spontaneously broken, and so on. In this series, we will endeavour to discuss each and every symmetry of the Standard Model, and classify them according to each of the categories above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Part I, we will give a schematic overview of the structure of the Standard Model and its gauge symmetries. In Parts II and III we will consider global continuous symmetries, first from the perspective of the low-energy theory, and then from the perspective of the high-energy theory. In Part IV we will consider the discrete symmetries $C$, $P$, and $T$, and in Part V we will collect these results together and discuss how they are affected by some extensions to the theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gauge-symmetries&#34;&gt;Gauge Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting point for the construction of the Standard Model is the gauge group&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \ , $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the first factor represents the colour symmetry of &lt;strong&gt;quantum chromodynamics (QCD)&lt;/strong&gt;, and the second two factors (known as weak isospin and hypercharge) represent the symmetry of the &lt;strong&gt;electroweak&lt;/strong&gt; interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-field-content&#34;&gt;The Field Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standard Model contains gauge bosons corresponding to each of the gauge groups described above, along with $n_g = 3$ generations of Weyl fermions in the following representations, as well as a single scalar field, the Higgs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$SU(2)_L$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$U(1)_Y$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Q_L$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 1/6$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$u_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 2/3$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$d_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1/3$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$L_L$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1/2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$e_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$\nu_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$\phi$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 1/2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lagrangian&#34;&gt;The Lagrangian&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most general renormalizable Lagrangian with the above gauge symmetry and field content is the Standard Model. We can group the terms in the Lagrangian into four classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the gauge fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the fermions, including coupling to the gauge fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the Higgs and Higgs self-interactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yukawa couplings between the fermions and the Higgs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schematically, this Lagrangian is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \begin{align} \mathcal{L} = &amp;amp;-\frac{1}{4} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^{a\mu \nu} \\ &amp;amp;+ \bar{\psi} i  \gamma^\mu D_\mu \psi \\ &amp;amp;+ |D_\mu \phi|^2 - V(\phi) \\ &amp;amp;- Y_d \bar{Q}_L \phi d_R - Y_u \bar{Q}_{L} \phi^c u_R + \mathrm{h.c.} \\ &amp;amp;- Y_e \bar{L}_L \phi e_R - Y_\nu \bar{L}_{L} \phi^c \nu_R + \mathrm{h.c.} \end{align} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an additional class of term one can add to the Lagrangian whose effects are more subtle. These are the theta terms, one for each factor of the gauge group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\theta =  \frac{\theta g^2}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will ignore these terms until Part IV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exact-symmetries&#34;&gt;Exact Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lagrangian above has many approximate global symmetries which we will discuss in due course. The extent to which these symmetries are approximate is dictated by the various parameters of the theory. For general choices of these parameters (and in reality) the Standard Model has only two exact global continuous symmetries. These are &lt;strong&gt;baryon number&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;lepton number&lt;/strong&gt;. They are not enforced upon the theory &amp;mdash; rather, it is simply not possible to write down renormalizable terms respecting the overall gauge symmetry which violate baryon or lepton number. We sometimes say such symmetries are &lt;strong&gt;accidental&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spontaneous-symmetry-breaking&#34;&gt;Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A symmetry is spontaneously broken if it is respected by the Lagrangian but not by the vacuum of the theory. Spontaneous symmetry breaking is typically caused by fields acquiring a non-zero expectation value in the vacuum. In the Standard Model, there are two sources of spontaneous symmetry breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Higgs field $\phi$ acquires a non-zero VEV. This breaks the gauge symmetry thus:
$$ SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \to SU(3)_C \times U(1)_Q \ .$$
It also breaks some approximate global symmetries. This is known as &lt;strong&gt;electroweak symmetry breaking&lt;/strong&gt;. The unbroken $U(1)_Q$ symmetry is the symmetry of &lt;strong&gt;quantum electrodynamics (QED)&lt;/strong&gt;. We will discuss this further in Part III.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a lower energy scale, the quark bilinears $\bar{q}q$ acquire a non-zero VEV (equal in magnitude for each flavour). This breaks no further gauge symmetries, but does break some approximate global symmetries. This is known as &lt;strong&gt;chiral symmetry breaking&lt;/strong&gt;. We will discuss this further in Part II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;anomalies&#34;&gt;Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A symmetry is anomalous if it is respected by the Lagrangian but not by the path integral measure. For a symmetry $H$ with generators $t^a$ and a gauge symmetry $G$ with generators $T^a$, we say that $H$ suffers a $G$-anomaly if the &lt;strong&gt;anomaly coefficient&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathrm{tr}(\gamma^5 t^a \{T^b, T^c\}) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is non-zero. In principle it is possible for anomalies to arise from diagrams with three different currents, but this cannot happen in the Standard Model since such diagrams always involve exactly one generator of $SU(2)_L$ or $SU(3)_C$, which is traceless. It is a somewhat magical feature of the Standard Model, which one should check from the table of field representations above, that no gauge symmetry $H$ suffers a $G$-anomaly for any gauge symmetry $G$. Indeed, this is necessary for the theory to be consistent. Nevertheless, there are several global symmetries $H$ which suffer $G$-anomalies, as we shall see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
