<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | George Johnson</title>
    <link>/blog/</link>
      <atom:link href="/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu7bc565721a69e427bf94bf1315c635aa_13529_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/blog/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Irrotational Vector Fields Conservative? An Excursion into Algebraic Topology</title>
      <link>/blog/cohomology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/cohomology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;conservative-and-irrotational-vector-fields&#34;&gt;Conservative and Irrotational Vector Fields&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smooth vector field $\mathbf{F}$ in $\mathbb{R}^3$ is known as &lt;strong&gt;conservative&lt;/strong&gt; if it can be written as the gradient of a scalar field: $\mathbf{F} = \nabla f$. A vector field is termed &lt;strong&gt;irrotational&lt;/strong&gt; if it has zero curl: $\nabla \times \mathbf{F} = \mathbf{0}$. It is not hard to check that all conservative vector fields are irrotational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The converse also happens to be true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theorem 1:&lt;/em&gt; an irrotational vector field on $\mathbb{R}^3$ is conservative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One consequence of this result is that the line integral of an irrotational field between any two points is independent of the path taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-exception&#34;&gt;An Exception&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In electromagnetism, the magnetic field around a static current-carrying wire obeys Ampère&amp;rsquo;s Law: $\nabla \times \mathbf{B} = \mathbf{0}$. We may thus hope to write the magnetic field in terms of a so-called magnetic scalar potential, $\mathbf{B} = \nabla \psi$. However, it is clear from the circulating nature of the solution,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathbf{B}= \frac{\mu_0 I}{2 \pi r} \mathbf{e}_\phi  \ ,$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that the integral of $\mathbf{B}$ along a circle enclosing the wire is non-zero. In fact an everywhere-defined scalar potential does not exist. This apparent conflict with Theorem 1 can be resolved in one of two ways: either we note that $\mathbf{B}$ fails to be irrotational inside the wire, where it obeys the equation $\nabla \times \mathbf{B} = \mu_0 \mathbf{J}$; or we consider the wire not to be part of our space, and treat our field as defined not on all of $\mathbb{R}^3$ (as required for the theorem to hold), but on $\mathbb{R}^3 \setminus \mathrm{line}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking this latter viewpoint, we are led to an interesting question: what features of a space permit or prevent us from expressing irrotational vector fields as the gradient of scalar fields? What is the pertinent difference between $\mathbb{R}^3$ and $\mathbb{R}^3 \setminus \mathrm{line}$ such that Theorem 1 holds for one but not the other? The answer to this question lies in the domain of topology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;de-rhams-theorem&#34;&gt;De Rham&amp;rsquo;s Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a space $M$, we can ask not just whether or not Theorem 1 holds on $M$, but indeed &lt;em&gt;to what extent&lt;/em&gt; the theorem holds. To be precise, let us define an equivalence relation on the set of all vector fields on $M$ by identifying $\mathbf{F}$ and $\mathbf{G}$ if their difference is the gradient of a scalar field: $\mathbf{F} \sim \mathbf{G} \iff \mathbf{F} - \mathbf{G} = \nabla f$. This relation partitions the set of all vector fields on our space into classes. The space of all such classes is known as the &lt;strong&gt;first de Rham cohomology group&lt;/strong&gt; $H^1(M)$. Thus, Theorem 1 above can be recast in this language as the statement that for $\mathbb{R}^3$ only one equivalence class exists, or $H^1(\mathbb{R}^3) = \{0\}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central result of this analysis is de Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem, which relates this cohomology group to the topology of our space, as described by the &lt;strong&gt;first homology group&lt;/strong&gt; $H_1(M)$. This is a measure of the number of loops in our space which do not form the boundary of any surface. For example, every loop in $\mathbb{R}^3$ can be thought of as the edge of some disc. However, a loop in $N = \mathbb{R}^3 \setminus \mathrm{line}$ that encircles the missing line bounds no surface (that lies entirely in the space). We thus say that $H_1(\mathbb{R}^3) = \{0\}$, whilst $H_1(N) = \mathbb{R}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the names imply, there also exist higher homology and cohomology groups. Indeed (as we will discuss later) we can define $H_r(M)$ and $H^r(M)$ for $r \leq n$, the dimension of our space. De Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem makes a remarkably simple statement about them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theorem 2:&lt;/em&gt; the $r^\mathrm{th}$ cohomology group and $r^\mathrm{th}$ homology group of a space $M$ are isomorphic: $ H^r(M) \cong H_r(M) $.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the trivial first homology of $\mathbb{R}^3$, in conjunction with de Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem, implies Theorem 1 above. Moreover, we also have that $H^1(N) = \mathbb{R}$, which means that any irrotational vector field on $N$ can be written in the form $\mathbf{F} = \mathbf{B}_I + \nabla f$, where $\mathbf{B}_I$ (with $I \in H^1(N) = \mathbb{R})$ is a one-parameter family of irrotational fields. The magnetic fields of the previous section serve as one such family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;real-or-integer-homology&#34;&gt;Real or Integer Homology?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The homology groups that appear in de Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem are defined with real coefficients, and may more explicitly be written $H_r(M;\mathbb{R})$. In other contexts, we more commonly work with the &lt;strong&gt;integral homology&lt;/strong&gt; groups $H_r(M;\mathbb{Z})$, which are defined with integer coefficients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integral homology of a space is a somewhat &amp;lsquo;finer&amp;rsquo; topological invariant, and indeed determines the real homology uniquely. In particular, where an integral homology group is a direct sum of $k$ copies of $\mathbb{Z}$ and a finite abelian group, the corresponding real homology group will simply be $\mathbb{R}^k$. This extra finite group &amp;mdash; known as the torsion subgroup &amp;mdash; describes non-trivial loops that the real homology does not detect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, it is possible for a space to have non-trivial first (integral) homology group and yet nevertheless have the property that all irrotational vector fields are conservative. Perhaps the simplest example is the space $X = \mathbb{R}P^2 \times \mathbb{R}$. This is homotopy equivalent to the real projective plane $\mathbb{R}P^2$ and hence has first homology group $H_1(X;\mathbb{Z}) = \mathbb{Z}_2$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;homology-or-homotopy&#34;&gt;Homology or Homotopy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes said that irrotational vector fields are conservative when the domain of the field is &lt;strong&gt;simply connected&lt;/strong&gt;. To be simply connected is to have trivial &lt;strong&gt;first homotopy group&lt;/strong&gt;, $\pi_1$. Like the first homology group, the first homotopy group in some sense measures the non-trivial loops in our space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the first homology and first homotopy groups are in general different. A relation between them is provided by the Hurewicz theorem, which states that the first (integral) homology group is the Abelianisation of the first homotopy group &amp;mdash; that is, the quotient of $\pi_1$ under the equivalence relation $xy \sim yx$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, if our space is simply connected, then it also has trivial first homology group, and irrotational vector fields are conservative, as is claimed. However, the above discussion shows that simple connectedness isn&amp;rsquo;t a necessary condition for this property to hold. Indeed, any space whose first homotopy group has trivial Abelianisation will have this property. Such groups as known as &lt;strong&gt;perfect groups&lt;/strong&gt;, and are in some sense maximally non-Abelian. The smallest non-trivial example is the alternating group $A_5$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important example of a space with perfect fundamental group is the &lt;strong&gt;Poincaré homology sphere&lt;/strong&gt;. This is obtained as the quotient of $SO(3)$ &amp;mdash; the rotational symmetries of 3D space &amp;mdash; by the icosahedral group $I \cong A_5$ &amp;mdash; the rotational symmetries of the icosahedron. This quotient can hence be thought of as the space of all geometrically distinguishable orientations of the icosahedron. Passing to the double cover of both groups, we can also write this as the quotient $Y = S^3 / 2I$, where $2I$ is the binary icosahedral group (a perfect group also). This space has $\pi_1(Y) = 2I$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a great deal of interesting mathematics concerning such &amp;lsquo;spheres&amp;rsquo; with perfect $\pi_1$. However, if we seek a space which is not simply connected but for which irrotational vector fields are conservative, a more straightforward example would simply exploit the difference between real and integral homology. For example, the space $X = \mathbb{R}P^2 \times \mathbb{R}$ considered in the previous section has $\pi_1(X) = H_1(X;\mathbb{Z}) = \mathbb{Z}_2$, and yet the first de Rham cohomology group of this space is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;generalising-higher-cohomology&#34;&gt;Generalising: Higher Cohomology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the curl of the gradient of any scalar field is zero, so the divergence of the curl of any vector field is zero. So, just as above, we can ask: to what extent can a &lt;strong&gt;solenoidal vector field&lt;/strong&gt; (one with zero divergence) be written as the curl of another vector field? The answer to this question depends on the space $M$ our fields live on&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, and is quantified by the second de Rham cohomology group, $H^2(M)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also define higher homology groups. Where the first homology group quantifies the number of non-trivial loops in our space, the second homology group $H_2(M)$ quantifies the non-trivial closed surfaces (or more precisely, those surfaces which are not the boundaries of some volume). All closed surfaces in $\mathbb{R}^3$ bound their interior, and so $H_2(\mathbb{R}^3) = \{0\}$. However, remove a point from $\mathbb{R}^3$ and this is no longer the case &amp;mdash; surfaces which enclose this point are not the boundaries of any volume. We hence have $H_2(\mathbb{R}^3 \setminus \mathrm{point}) = \mathbb{R}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we noted above, de Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem states that the $r^\mathrm{th}$ homology and $r^\mathrm{th}$ cohomology groups of a space are isomorphic. Thus, there exist solenoidal fields on $\mathbb{R}^3 \setminus \mathrm{point}$ which cannot be written as the curl of another vector field. The magnetic field around a magnetic monopole is an example of such a field. This fact (after some explication) leads to a famous observation of Dirac, that the existence of a magnetic monopole in our universe would necessitate the quantisation of electric charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no relation between higher homology and homotopy groups in general (although the Hurewicz theorem provides a condition under which they are isomorphic). Thus, one should not make the mistake of invoking the second homotopy group $\pi_2$ to conclude that a vector potential must exist, as the following example illustrates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let $Z$ be the space $T^2 \times \mathbb{R}$, where $T^2$ is the 2-torus. Then $H_2(Z) = \mathbb{R}$ but $\pi_2(Z) = \{0\}$. Despite having trivial second homotopy group, there exist solenoidal fields on $Z$ which cannot be written as the curl of another vector field. The simplest example of such a field is $\mathbf{B} = B \mathbf{e}_3$, corresponding to a constant vector field pointing along the $\mathbb{R}$ direction. Integrating this field over the torus at some fixed $z \in \mathbb{R}$ gives a positive number, yet the integral of any curl over such a surface must be zero by Stokes&#39; theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a final chapter to this story which is rarely discussed. The third homology group of a space describes the number of &amp;lsquo;non-trivial volumes&amp;rsquo;. The third de Rham cohomlogy group describes the extent to which a scalar field can be written as the divergence of a vector field. On $\mathbb{R}^3$ this is always possible &amp;mdash; for example, the field $f = c$ can be written as the divergence of $\mathbf{F} = c x \mathbf{e}_1$. On topologically less trivial spaces, such as the 3-sphere, no such vector field exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; In order to cast the discussion of this section into the familiar language of vector calculus, we shall need to assume that our space $M$ is orientable. This technical requirement allows us to define the Hodge star operator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-words&#34;&gt;Final Words&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion above has repeatedly featured the curl of a vector field, and so has been inherently three-dimensional. Nevertheless, there is a simple generalisation of the above ideas to higher dimensions. The curl is replaced by a more general operator, the &lt;strong&gt;exterior derivative&lt;/strong&gt;. The cohomology groups of a given space capture the extent to which certain fields (namely, differential forms) can be expressed as the exterior derivative of others. As in three dimensions, these groups are isomorphic to the corresponding homology groups, which describe the number and nature of the holes in our space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This connection between calculus and topology has far-reaching implications, well beyond the seemingly innocuous question we first asked about conservative and irrotational vector fields.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Euler&#39;s Polyhedron Formula and the Gauss-Bonnet Theorem</title>
      <link>/blog/polyhedron/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/polyhedron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;eulers-polyhedron-formula&#34;&gt;Euler&amp;rsquo;s Polyhedron Formula&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a wonderful theorem due to Euler (1752) which states that for a convex polyhedron with $V$ vertices, $E$ edges, and $F$ faces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V - E + F = 2 \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post we will sketch a proof of this result, and then extend it to non-convex polyhedra. Our starting point will be a result in the subject of spherical geometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-angle-defect-formula&#34;&gt;The Angle Defect Formula&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a triangle drawn on the plane, the sum of the interior angles is $\pi$. For a triangle drawn on the surface of a unit sphere, whose sides are arcs of great circles, the internal angles $\alpha,\beta,\gamma$ satisfy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi = \text{area of triangle} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prove this, consider extending the sides of the triangle into three great circles. These divide the sphere into eight regions. By the symmetry of the figure under the exchange of antipodal points, our triangle and the three faces which neighbour it constitute exactly half the area of the sphere. The total area of these four regions is hence $2 \pi$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now our triangle together with any one of the three neighbouring regions form the surface of a spherical wedge. A wedge of angle $\theta$ has surface area $2 \theta$ (this gives an area $4 \pi$ when $\theta = 2 \pi$). If we consider the three possible wedges in turn, their total area is hence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 2(\alpha + \beta + \gamma) \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this total area can be written as the sum of the areas of those regions neighbouring our triangle, plus thrice the area of the triangle. Since we know that the four regions together have an area of $2 \pi$, we can rearrange for the area of our triangle, giving the angle defect formula quoted above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-euler&#34;&gt;Back to Euler&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the angle defect formula to hand, we can embark on our proof of Euler&amp;rsquo;s formula. Given any convex polyhedron, choose a point in its interior as the origin and form the projection onto the surface of the unit sphere. Deform the edges so that they form the arcs of great circles (that this is always possible is plausible, though we will not prove it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any face with four or more vertices, consider inserting a new edge. This adds precisely one face and one edge, and hence leaves unchanged the quantity $\chi = V - E + F$. We can hence, without loss of generality, take our polyhedron to be constructed from triangular faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For such a polyhedron, each face has three edges, and each edge is shared by two faces. Thus we can relate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ E = \frac{3}{2} F  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each triangular face, we can apply the angle defect formula. Summing over all faces, we find&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sum_F (\alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi) = \text{area of sphere} = 4 \pi  \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sum over all faces of all internal angles of each face can be reorganised as a sum over all vertices of all angles at each vertex. But the angles at a vertex sum to $2 \pi$, and hence the above formula reads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 2 \pi V - \pi F = 4 \pi \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the results above can be combined to give Euler&amp;rsquo;s formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V - E + F = 2  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;generalising-the-angle-defect-formula&#34;&gt;Generalising the Angle Defect Formula&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those familiar with Riemannian geometry, the notion of an angle defect may appear connected with the notion of parallel transport. Indeed, the failure of a vector to return to itself upon parallel transport around some small rectangle seems to correspond to the failure of the interior angles to sum to $2 \pi$. But this failure can also be quantified by the Riemann tensor, a measure of the curvature of the space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may thus hope to generalise the angle defect formula to arbitrary curved surfaces thus. Let $K$ be an appropriate scalar curvature, which takes the value $1$ for the unit sphere. Let $\alpha,\beta,\gamma$ be the internal angles of a triangle $\triangle$ on this surface, whose edges are geodesics. Then we postulate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi = \int_{\triangle} K \ \mathrm{d}A \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This formula turns out to be true &amp;mdash; it is called the local Gauss-Bonnet theorem, and holds with $K$ the Gauss curvature of the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-gauss-bonnet-theorem&#34;&gt;The Gauss-Bonnet Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this new formula to hand, we can repeat the previous steps for any polyhedron, not necessarily a convex one. First map the polyhedron to some smooth surface, topologically equivalent to it. Deform the edges so that they are geodesics on this surface, and insert new edges so that all faces are triangular. We then have $E = 3F/2$ as before, but now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sum_F (\alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi) = \int K \ \mathrm{d}A \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reorganising the sum over faces as a sum over vertices, this gives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 2 \pi V - \pi F = \int K \ \mathrm{d}A  \ , $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and altogether we have the global Gauss-Bonnet theorem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V - E + F = \frac{1}{2 \pi} \int K \ \mathrm{d}A  \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;musings&#34;&gt;Musings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At once this theorem tells us two pretty facts about polyhedra and curved surfaces. Firstly, it implies that for any two polyhedra which are topologically equivalent, the quantity $\chi = V - E + F$ &amp;mdash; known as the Euler characteristic &amp;mdash; must take the same value, since both can be mapped to the same surface with fixed integrated curvature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it implies that for any two smooth surfaces which are topologically equivalent, the integrated curvature must take the same value, since both surfaces can be triangulated with the same polyhedron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Said more succinctly, the integrated curvature and the Euler characteristic are both &lt;strong&gt;topological invariants&lt;/strong&gt; of closed surfaces, equal to one another by the Gauss-Bonnet theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Even Degree Graph Partition</title>
      <link>/blog/partition/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/partition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given any finite graph $G$, can we partition the vertex set $V = V_1 \cup V_2$ such that in the induced subgraphs $G[V_1]$, $G[V_2]$ every vertex has even degree? If every degree in the original graph is even, we are done, since we can take $V_1 = V$, $V_2 = \varnothing$. We can suppose therefore that at least one vertex in $G$ has odd degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is natural to attempt to prove this result by induction, on the number of vertices in $G$ perhaps. So suppose $|G| = n$ and that the result is true for graphs of order $n-1$. We can remove a vertex $v$ from $G$ and use the inductive hypothesis to partition the remaining vertices so that they all have even degree in their respective subgraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficulty comes when we reintroduce $v$. Suppose we assign $v$ to the subset $V_1$. Then any neighbours of $v$ in $V_1$ will gain an extra edge, and hence have odd degree. We can therefore only preserve the even degree condition if one of the two subsets contains no neighbours of $v$. But there seems to be no way to arrange for this in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-idea&#34;&gt;An Idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem, at a glance, that an inductive argument is not appropriate in this case. However, we have not used the full might of the inductive hypothesis, which states that the result is true for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; graphs of order $n-1$, not just $G - v$. We may thus hope to construct and then partition a different graph $G&#39;$ of order $n-1$, such that when we reintroduce $v$ &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; pass back to the original set of edges, the degrees of the vertices are unchanged (modulo two, at least).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first note that $v$ itself must have even degree in the subgraph it eventually belongs to. We can ensure this by choosing $v$ to be a vertex of odd degree in $G$ (as noted above, such a choice is possible without loss of generality). Then $v$ must have an even number of neighbours in either $V_1$ or $V_2$ &amp;mdash; let&amp;rsquo;s say it&amp;rsquo;s $V_1$ &amp;mdash; and we can hence choose to reintroduce $v$ to $V_1$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, how can we contruct the graph $G&#39;$ we speculated about above? Since reintroducing $v$ introduces an extra edge to each of its neighbours in $V_1$, we would like to construct a graph such that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any neighbour of $v$ in $V_1$ has a different degree modulo two in $(G-v)[V_1]$ and $G&#39;[V_1]$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any neighbour of $v$ in $V_2$ has the same degree modulo two in $(G-v)[V_2]$ and $G&#39;[V_2]$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This looks a little tricky, since the partition $V_1 \cup V_2$ we take will depend on the graph $G&#39;$ we construct. Denote the neighbours of $v$ by $\Gamma(v)$ and focus on the graph $G[\Gamma(v)]$. Restrict the partitions to these vertices: $W_i = V_i \cap \Gamma(v)$. We know that $|W_1|$ is even and $|W_2|$ is odd. Consider therefore that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$w \in W_1$ has a different number of neighbours and non-neighbours (modulo two) in $G[W_1]$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$w \in W_2$ has the same number of neighbours and non-neighbours (modulo two) in $G[W_2]$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An idea now presents itself: delete every edge in $G[\Gamma(v)]$ and introduce an edge wherever there wasn&amp;rsquo;t one. Such a construction is known as the &lt;strong&gt;complement&lt;/strong&gt; of the graph $G[\Gamma(v)]$. By virtue of the above two facts, we have hereby changed the degree of every vertex in $G[W_1]$ and left unchanged the degree of every vertex in $G[W_2]$ (modulo two). This remains true when we reattach the rest of the graph $G-v$. But this is precisely what we wanted to achieve!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-proof&#34;&gt;A Proof&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us put these ideas together. Given a graph $G$ of order $n$, choose a vertex $v$ of odd degree (if no such vertex exists, we are done). From $G-v$ construct the graph $G&#39;$ by deleting edges between those elements $v_1, v_2$ of $\Gamma(v)$ with $v_1 v_2 \in E(G)$ and introducing edges between those elements $v_1, v_2$ of $\Gamma(v)$ with $v_1 v_2 \notin E(G)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apply the inductive hypothesis to $G&#39;$. Suppose that $v$ has an even number of neighbours in $V_1$ (if not, it has an even number of neighbours in $V_2$). Then the subsets $V_1 \cup \{ v \}$ and $V_2$ consitute a partition of $V$ such that every vertex in the induced subgraphs has even degree .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proof is completed by noting that the result is clearly true for $n=1$.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model V: Summary and Extensions</title>
      <link>/blog/sm5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;extensions&#34;&gt;Extensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series we have discussed the symmetries of the Standard Model in its &amp;lsquo;standard&amp;rsquo; form. Some aspects of the theory, such as the Higgs sector and the neutrino mass terms, have not been definitively established, and it is quite possible that nature behave somewhat differently from the present model. For example, electroweak symmetry could be broken by an extended sector, containing the Higgs boson alongside other scalar fields. Likewise, the neutrino masses may receive contributions (solely or partially) from Majorana terms. The current model is merely the simplest one consistent with current experimental constraints, but future experiments may demand that we extend our model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, even at present there are several theoretical and experimental motivations for such extensions. Attempts to understand why the gauge group takes the form it does, why there are three generations, and why each generation has the structure it does, lead naturally to grand unified theories, with a single simple gauge group. On the other hand, the existence of dark matter and the apparent non-existence of the QCD theta term motivate the addition of further fields to the theory. In this final part of the series we will look at some natural extensions of the Standard Model, and how they impact its symmetries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;majorana-neutrinos&#34;&gt;Majorana Neutrinos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is in fact one term we have neglected to add to the Lagrangian throughout this series, consistent with both renormalizability and the gauge symmetry of the theory. This is the Majorana mass term for the right-handed neutrinos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_m = -m \epsilon^{ab} \nu^a_R \nu^b_R + \mathrm{h.c.}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here $m$ is a matrix in flavour space. Such a term exists only for the right-handed neutrinos since they are the only fields in the theory which transform as singlets under each factor of the gauge group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Majorana mass term violates lepton number (and also breaks explicitly the $T^3_R$ subgroup of $SU(2)_R$). Thus, with the inclusion of this term the theory possesses no non-anomalous exact global symmetries ($B-L$ being the only such symmetry previously). The only exact anomalous symmetry of our new Lagrangian is baryon number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diagonalisation of the mass terms is slightly more complicated in this case, though it is straightforward to sketch the effect on the discrete symmetries. We note that $\mathcal{L}_m$ above is not invariant under neutrino rephasings, unlike the diagonalised Yukawa mass terms. Thus, after diagonalisation, the mass terms possess only a $U(1)^3$ flavour symmetry (corresponding to charged lepton rephasings), and this allows us to remove only three phases from the PMNS matrix. There are thus three $CP$-violating phases in the lepton sector in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;axions&#34;&gt;Axions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-higgs-doublets&#34;&gt;Two Higgs Doublets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the summary tables from the previous parts of the series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QED ($\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QCD and QED&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T_R^1$ and $T_R^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T^1$ and $T^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B+L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electroweak&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B-L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QCD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Electroweak&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QED&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$P$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T$ or $CP$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{CKM} = \theta_{PMNS} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model IV: Discrete Symmetries</title>
      <link>/blog/sm4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three discrete &amp;lsquo;spacetime&amp;rsquo; symmetries of importance in any quantum field theory. These are &lt;strong&gt;charge conjugation&lt;/strong&gt; $C$, &lt;strong&gt;parity&lt;/strong&gt; $P$, and &lt;strong&gt;time-reversal&lt;/strong&gt; $T$. The CPT theorem states that any Lorentz-invariant local quantum field theory will be invariant under the product operation $CPT$. We will hence consider $CP$ and $T$ to be equivalent symmetry operations. None of these symmetries is anomalous nor spontaneously broken in the Standard Model. We will hence discuss in turn the sectors of the theory in which they are respected or violated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-kinetic-terms&#34;&gt;The Kinetic Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without coupling the fermions to the $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$ gauge fields, we find that the kinetic terms for the gauge fields, the fermions, and the Higgs (that is, all terms except the Yukawa terms) are invariant under all three discrete symmetries. However, since the left- and right-handed fermions couple differently under $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, these coupling terms violate both $C$ and $P$. They nevertheless preserve the combined symmetry $CP$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since $CP$ is the only discrete symmetry respected by the kinetic terms, we will focus on this symmetry alone in the next two sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-yukawa-terms-----quarks&#34;&gt;The Yukawa Terms &amp;mdash; Quarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We established in Part III that the Yukawa matrices $Y_u, Y_d$ could be taken without loss of generality to be Hermitian and positive semi-definite, and were uniquely determined by this requirement. We will assume this convention henceforth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The action of $CP$ on the Yukawa terms is a symmetry if $Y_u$ and $Y_d$ are real matrices. Generically they will not be. However, in unitarity gauge we can independently rotate (vectorially) the up-type and down-type quarks to diagonalise the Yukawa matrices: take
$u_{L,R} \to U_u u_{L,R}$ and $d_{L,R} \to U_d d_{L,R}$ so that
$$ U_u^\dagger Y_u U_u = D_u \quad \mathrm{and} \quad U_d^\dagger Y_d U_d = D_d  \ . $$
The eigenvalues of these matrices are the (real and non-negative) masses of the quarks. After such a rotation, the Yukawa terms become real and hence $CP$-symmetric, and additionally enjoy a $U(1)^6$ flavour symmetry (at the least).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This field redefinition disturbs only one other term in the Lagrangian, which is the coupling of the weak charged current to the charged $W^\pm$ bosons. In particular:
$$ \bar{u}_L \gamma^\mu d_L \to \bar{u}_L U _u^\dagger U_d \gamma^\mu d_L  \ . $$
The matrix $V = U_u^\dagger U_d$ is known as the CKM matrix. A general unitary matrix has $n_g^2$ real parameters, of which $n_g(n_g+1)/2$ are complex phases. We can use the aforementioned freedom to rephase our quarks without disturbing the Yukawa terms to reduce the number of parameters in this matrix: $V \to U^\dagger V$ or $V \to V U$ where $U = \mathrm{diag}(e^{i \alpha}, e^{i \beta}, e^{i \gamma})$. Note that the $U(1)_B$ subgroup of $U(1)^6$ has trivial action on $V$. We can thus reduce the nine parameters in $V$ down to four (not three), of which one must be a complex phase, known as the CKM phase. All four parameterers are non-zero in the Standard Model. The CKM phase violates $CP$. The other three real parameters characterise the size of the mixing between quark flavours. Since these are all non-zero, there are no global flavour symmetries in the quark sector besides the flavour-blind $U(1)_B$, as we alluded to in Part III.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We note that if $g = 0$, there is no CP violation, even if our Lagrangian originally had complex Yukawa matrices (this illustrates that whilst no discrete symmetries may be initially apparent, an appropriate field redefinition can reveal one). As such, though we began this section considering the symmetries of the Yukawa terms, we say that CP violation from the CKM phase is a &lt;em&gt;weak interaction effect&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; show that with $n_g$ generations, the CKM matrix contains $(n_g-1)(n_g-2)/2$ complex phases. Conclude that three generations is the minimum required for weak CP violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-yukawa-terms-----leptons&#34;&gt;The Yukawa Terms &amp;mdash; Leptons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above analysis applies identically to the lepton sector. The phase in the mixing matrix is known as the PMNS phase in this case, rather than the CKM phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We note that if we take $Y_\nu = 0$, so that the neutrinos are massless, then we can diagonalise the Yukawa matrices without disturbing the weak charged current (simply choose $U_\nu = U_e$). In this case $CP$ will be exact, and in addition there will be an exact $U(1)^3$ flavour symmetry, corresponding to conservation of lepton number in each generation. For a time it was thought that the neutrinos were exactly massless, and that these were indeed exact symmetries. It is now known this is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More generally, we see that we can arrange for $V = I$ so long as the Yukawa matrices can be simultaneously diagonalised. For Hermitian matrices (and diagonalisable matrices more generally) this is equivalent to $[Y_e, Y_\nu] = 0$. Thus if the Yukawa matrices commute, both $CP$ and individual lepton number will be symmetries of the theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, $CP$ alone will be a symmetry under weaker requirements. Any degeneracy of eigenvalue in one of the two Yukawa matrices bestows the Yukawa terms with an additional $SU(2)$ symmetry (alongside $U(1)^6$). This is sufficient to remove the single complex phase for $n_g = 3$. Thus, with three generations, there will be no weak CP violation if there is a single pair of degenerate charged leptons &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; neutrinos (and a single pair of degenerate up-type quarks &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; down-type quarks). For $n_g = 3$, a degenerate eigenvalue implies $\det[Y_e, Y_\nu] = 0$. Thus we can claim that $\theta_{PMNS}$ is physical if $\det[Y_e, Y_\nu] \neq 0$ (and likewise for the quark sector).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phases $\theta_{CKM}$ and $\theta_{PMNS}$ are the two sources of &lt;strong&gt;weak CP violation&lt;/strong&gt; in the Standard Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-theta-terms&#34;&gt;The Theta Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an additional class of term one can add to the Standard Model Lagrangian that we mentioned in Part I but have ignored since then. These are the theta terms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\theta =  \frac{\theta g^2}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are precisely the terms that appear on the right-hand sides of anomalous current conservation equations, as we have seen in Parts II and III. They violate both $P$ and $T$ (and so $CP$), but not $C$. In general such terms can be removed by a field redefinition corresponding to an anomalous symmetry. However, since we have made various such transformations in order to simplify the Yukawa terms, any attempts to remove the theta terms thus will appear to reintroduce symmetry-violating phases into other parts of the Lagrangian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, having exhausted chiral rotations of the right-handed fermions to make the Yukawa matrices Hermitian, and having exhausted vectorial rotations of the fermions to diagonalise the Yukawa matrices and subsequently simplify the CKM and PMNS matrices, the only transformations which remain for us to exploit are those which are genuine symmetries of the Lagrangian. However, to introduce or remove any theta term, such a symmetry must be anomalous. There is only one such symmetry, $B + L$, and hence in general only one theta term can be removed. Since the divergence of the corresponding current contains only $SU(2)_L$ and $U(1)_Y$ gauge fields, the QCD theta term cannot be removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that if one of the quarks is massless, then $U(1)_R$ (for that quark flavour) is a symmetry of the Lagrangian. Argue that in this case, we can remove the QCD theta term. We can thus claim that $\theta_{QCD}$ is physical if $\det(Y_u Y_d) \neq 0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It transpires, however, that the $U(1)_Y$ theta term is always unphysical. It can be seen that the theta terms are in fact total derivatives, and so their effects are non-perturbative. Whether they have any effect at all depends on whether there exist field configurations (that are pure gauge at infinity) such that this surface term is non-zero &amp;mdash; such configurations are known as &lt;strong&gt;instantons&lt;/strong&gt;. In four spacetime dimensions instantons exist if and only if the third homotopy group of the gauge group is non-trivial. Since $\pi_3(U(1)) = \{0\}$ and $\pi_3(SU(n)) = \mathbb{Z}$ for $n \geq 2$, there exist only $SU(3)_C$ and $SU(2)_L$ instantons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absence of $U(1)_Y$ instantons compels us to perform a $U(1)_{B+L}$ field redefinition that removes the $SU(2)_L$ theta term, leaving the QCD theta term as the only one with physical consequences. The phase $\theta_{QCD}$ is the sole source of &lt;strong&gt;strong CP violation&lt;/strong&gt; in the Standard Model (we reiterate that it also violates $P$). No effects of this term have yet been discovered, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since neither $C$, $P$, nor $T$ is anomalous nor spontaneously broken by the vacuum, we here classify these symmetries according to whether they are respected in the following three cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QCD: we set $g = g&#39; = 0$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electroweak: we set $g_s = 0$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QED: we set $g_s = 0$ and ignore the Higgs and massive gauge bosons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QCD&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Electroweak&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;QED&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$P$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T$ or $CP$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{QCD} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If $\theta_{CKM} = \theta_{PMNS} = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model III: The Higgs Sector</title>
      <link>/blog/sm3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this part of the series we will discuss the global symmetries of the full Standard Model Lagrangian. We will first consider the terms involving just the Higgs, then those coupling the Higgs to the fermions, and then those coupling the Higgs to the gauge bosons. Lastly, we will consider symmetries acting only on the fermion fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-higgs-potential&#34;&gt;The Higgs Potential&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Higgs Lagrangian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\phi = |D_\mu \phi|^2 + \mu^2 \phi^\dagger \phi - \lambda( \phi^\dagger \phi)^2  $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is by construction invariant under the gauge symmetry $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, where we take $Y = 1/2$ by convention and let $\phi$ transform in the fundamental of $SU(2)_L$. However, the Higgs potential is in fact invariant under a larger symmetry group. This is easiest to see by writing $\phi$ in terms of its real and imaginary parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \phi = \begin{pmatrix} \phi_2 + i \phi_1 \\ \phi_0 - i \phi_3 \end{pmatrix}  \ ,$$
so that
$$ \phi^\dagger \phi = \sum_i \phi_i^2  \ .$$
Then there is an obvious $O(4)$ symmetry. Ignoring discrete quotients, we have $O(4) = SU(2) \times SU(2)$. To see this decomposition explicitly in the case of the Higgs field, we can construct the matrix
$$ \Phi = \begin{pmatrix} \phi_0 + i \phi_3 &amp;amp;  \phi_2 + i \phi_1 \\ - \phi_2 + i \phi_1 &amp;amp; \phi_0 - i \phi_3 \end{pmatrix} = \phi_0 I + i \sum_i \phi_i \sigma_i \ . $$
Note that $\Phi = |\phi| U$ where $U \in SU(2)$. Then we have
$$ \phi^\dagger \phi = \frac{1}{2}\mathrm{tr}(\Phi^\dagger \Phi) \ ,$$
which is invariant under the transformation
$$ \Phi \to U_L \Phi U_R^\dagger \ ,$$
where $U_{L,R} \in SU(2)$  (one can check that if $U_{L,R}$ are allowed to lie in $U(2)$ instead, they do not generally preserve the form of $\Phi$ as a real multiple of a special unitary matrix). The reader can check that the left action on $\Phi$ corresponds precisely to the action of $SU(2)_L$ on the original field $\phi$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Higgs acquires a vacuum expectation value, so that $\Phi \propto I$, this symmetry group is spontaneously broken down to the diagonal subgroup, with $U_L = U_R$. This symmetry is known as &lt;strong&gt;custodial symmetry&lt;/strong&gt;, $SU(2)_V$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exactness-----the-yukawa-terms&#34;&gt;Exactness &amp;mdash; The Yukawa Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider first a single generation of quarks. The Yukawa terms are
$$ \mathcal{L}_y = -y_d \bar{Q}_L \phi d_R - y_u \epsilon^{ab}\bar{Q}_{La} \phi^*_b u_R  +\mathrm{h.c.}  $$
By construction this Lagrangian is invariant under $SU(2)_L$, but does not appear to be invariant under $SU(2)_R$ (defined to act on doublets of right-handed fermions analogously to $SU(2)_L$). However, in the case that $y_u = y_d = y$, one can write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_y = -y \bar{Q}_L \Phi Q_R + \mathrm{h.c.} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is evidently invariant under $SU(2)_R$. With multiple generations, the complex numbers $y_u,y_d$ become complex matrices, which we will denote $Y_u,Y_d$. As above, $SU(2)_R$ will be a symmetry if $Y_u = Y_d$. However, since we can freely rotate the right-handed down-type quarks amongst themselves without disturbing any other term in the Lagrangian (and likewise for the right-handed up-type quarks), this requirement is a little too strict. In fact, $SU(2)_R$ will be a symmetry provided $Y_u$ and $Y_d$ are related by right-multiplication by a unitary matrix. In the case of a single generation, this just requires that $|y_u| = |y_d|$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that any square matrix $Y$ can be written as the product $HU$ where $H$ is Hermitian and positive semi-definite and $U$ is unitary. This is known as polar decomposition, and defines $H$ uniquely. We can hence use the freedom to rotate the right-handed fermions to ensure, without loss of generality, that the Yukawa matrices are Hermitian and positive semi-definite. With this convention, $SU(2)_R$ is a symmetry if and only if $Y_u = Y_d$ and $Y_e = Y_\nu$. This condition does not hold in reality, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since $SU(2)_L$ is always a symmetry of the Yukawa terms, the very same condition is necessary and sufficient for custodial $SU(2)_V$ to be exact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that the above condition can be expressed in a convention-independent manner as
$$ Y_u^\dagger Y_u = Y_d^\dagger Y_d \quad \mathrm{and} \quad  Y_e^\dagger Y_e = Y_\nu^\dagger Y_\nu \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exactness-----kinetic-terms-and-hypercharge&#34;&gt;Exactness &amp;mdash; Kinetic Terms and Hypercharge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ is truly the full symmetry group of the Higgs potential, and the first factor is the familiar gauged $SU(2)_L$ group, then hypercharge must be a subgroup of the second factor. Indeed, it is not too difficult to show that hypercharge acts on the Higgs $\Phi$ as the $T^3_R$ generator of $SU(2)_R$. However, hypercharge does not act on the quarks and leptons in this way. In fact, the generator of hypercharge can be written
$$ Y = T^3_R + B/2 - L/2 \ ,$$
where $B$ and $L$ are the generators of baryon number and lepton number respectively. Since only some subgroup of $SU(2)_R$ is gauged, and not the entirety of it, $SU(2)_R$ is not an exact symmetry of the theory (unless we set $g&#39; = 0$). To see this explicitly from the Lagrangian, we can consider the Higgs kinetic terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without gauge couplings, the kinetic terms of the Higgs are invariant under the full $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ symmetry group, just as the potential is. When we gauge the $SU(2)_L$ subgroup, the additional terms in the Lagrangian (coupling the Higgs to the gauge fields) are only invariant as a result of the global transformation properties of the gauge fields:
$$ W_\mu \to U W_\mu U^{-1} \ .$$
Thus, the problematic terms are those that involve the hypercharge gauge field $B_\mu$ (proportional to the matrix $T_R^3$), which does not transform under the action of the generators $T_R^1$ and $T_R^2$, nor commute with them:
$$ \begin{align} \mathrm{tr}(B^\mu \Phi^\dagger \Phi  B_\mu) \to \ &amp;amp;\mathrm{tr}(B^\mu (1 - i\alpha_iT_R^i)  \Phi^\dagger \Phi (1 + i\alpha_j T_R^j) B_\mu) \\&lt;br&gt;
\neq \ &amp;amp;\mathrm{tr}(B^\mu \Phi^\dagger \Phi  B_\mu) \ . \end{align}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; Show that the kinetic terms for the fermions also break $SU(2)_R$ explicitly when $g&#39; \neq 0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise: both the Yukawa terms and the coupling to the hypercharge gauge boson explicitly break the full $SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$ symmetry, but they leave intact both $SU(2)_L$ and the $T^3_R$ generator of $SU(2)_R$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fermion-symmetries-and-anomalies&#34;&gt;Fermion Symmetries and Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having considered the Higgs sector in some detail, we should ask whether there are any additional symmetries that act only on the fermions. If the Yukawa matrices are general (as they are in reality), the only possible symmetries are $U(1)$ rephasings of fermion flavours and chiralities. In fact, as we will justify more fully in Part IV, the only such symmetries are the vectorial and flavour-blind symmetries $U(1)_B$ and $U(1)_L$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though exact, both of these symmetries suffer an electroweak anomaly:
$$ \partial_\mu J_B^\mu = \partial_\mu J_L^\mu = \frac{n_g}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma}\left( g^2 W^a_{\mu \nu} W^a_{\rho \sigma} - {g&#39;}^2 B_{\mu \nu} B_{\rho \sigma}  \right) \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the divergences of the baryon number current and lepton number current are identical, we see that the combination of global symmetries $B - L$ is non-anomalous, and indeed is the only such exact global continuous symmetry in the Standard Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T_R^1$ and $T_R^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$T^1$ and $T^2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B+L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electroweak&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_{B-L}$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model II: The Quark Sector</title>
      <link>/blog/sm2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low energies, the Standard Model has unbroken gauge group $SU(3)_C \times U(1)_Q$. The heavy Higgs and massive gauge bosons can be ignored, leaving a theory of massless gauge bosons and several flavours of Dirac fermion. We will discuss the continuous global symmetries of this theory, focusing on the quark sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;flavour-symmetries&#34;&gt;Flavour Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With $n_f$ flavours of quark, the largest possible global symmetry group consists of independent unitary rotations of the left-handed quarks and the right-handed quarks, that is, $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R $. Such symmetries are sometimes called &lt;strong&gt;flavour symmetries&lt;/strong&gt;. Ignoring discrete symmetry quotients, this can be written
$$ SU(n_f)_L \times SU(n_f)_R \times U(1)_L \times U(1)_R  \ .$$
It is sometimes useful to rewrite left- and right-handed rotations in terms of rotations of both chiralities by the same amount and by opposite amounts. Such symmetries are called &lt;strong&gt;vector symmetries&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;axial symmetries&lt;/strong&gt; respectively. Thus we are tempted to write the above symmetry group as
$$ SU(n_f)_V \times SU(n_f)_A \times U(1)_V \times U(1)_A  \ .$$
In fact there is a small subtlety here. It is not the case that axial special unitary transformations form a group (they are not closed under composition). More precisely, we should think of $SU(n_f)_A$ as the coset $SU(n_f)_L \times SU(n_f)_R  / SU(n_f)_V$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exact-symmetries&#34;&gt;Exact Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a symmetry is exact when all the quarks are massless. If the quarks are not massless but all have the same mass, the vector symmetry is exact but none of the axial symmetries are. In the case that all the quark masses are different and non-zero, as in reality, the exact symmetry group is $U(1)_V^{n_f}$, corresponding to number conservation of each quark flavour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; show that if there are $n_0$ massless quarks and $n_i$ quarks of mass $m_i &amp;gt; 0$, then the exact symmetry group is
$$  U(n_0)_R \times U(n_0)_L \times \prod_i U(n_i)_V  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Standard Model, the lightest three quarks (the up, down, and strange) have sufficiently small masses that for $n_f = 3$ we can consider $U(n_f) \times U(n_f)$ to be a good approximate symmetry. It is an even better approximate symmetry for $n_f = 2$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spontaneous-symmetry-breaking&#34;&gt;Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All axial symmetries are broken by the vacuum due to the non-zero VEV of the quark bilinears $\bar{q}q$. Note that the broken gauge symmetry $SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$, acting on quarks, is in fact a subgroup of $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R$, provided we take $n_f = 6$. And indeed, spontaneous breaking of the axial symmetries translates into spontaneous breaking of the gauge symmetry down to $U(1)_Q$. One might wonder, therefore, whether the chiral condensate alone could be responsible for this pattern of symmetry breaking. However, this will naturally give the gauge bosons masses of order the QCD scale (around $100\ \mathrm{MeV})$ rather than the observed scale of $100\ \mathrm{GeV}$. Furthermore, the Higgs serves a second purpose in the Standard Model (in addition to breaking electroweak symmetry), which is to give masses to the quarks and leptons. Without the Higgs, the gauge symmetry can only be exact if all the quarks and leptons are massless, which is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;anomalies&#34;&gt;Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as being inexact and spontaneously broken by the vacuum, the axial symmetries are also anomalous. In particular, axial $U(1)_A$ suffers both a QCD anomaly and a QED anomaly. There is also one generator of axial $SU(n_f)_A$ which suffers a QED anomaly &amp;mdash; for $n_f = 3$ this is $\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$. The aforementioned QCD anomaly is the supposed explanation for the lack of a fourth ($n_f = 2$) or ninth ($n_f = 3$) light meson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might suspect that the QED anomaly suffered by $SU(n_f)_A$ would also raise the masses of some of the other light mesons. This is a rather complicated story which we will briefly discuss in Part IV. For the present moment we note that if we neglect electric charge ($e = 0$), the only anomalous symmetry is axial $U(1)_A$:
$$ \partial_\mu J_5^\mu = -\frac{n_f g_s^2}{32 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma}F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lepton-sector&#34;&gt;The Lepton Sector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle a similar study is warranted of the global continuous symmetries of the lepton sector. However, this is vastly more simple. Firstly, without the strong dynamics of QCD, there is no chiral condensate, so no spontaneous symmetry breaking. Secondly, the lepton masses are sufficiently different that no flavour symmetry can fairly be called approximate. We note, however, that to the extent that any $U(n_f)_L \times U(n_f)_R$ flavour symmetry &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be considered approximate, the axial symmetries would suffer a QED anomaly as in the quark case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exercise:&lt;/em&gt; As we stated in Part I, a generator $T$ of $SU(n_f)_A$ suffers a QED anomaly if $\mathrm{tr}(TQ^2) \neq 0$, where $Q$ is the generator of electric charge. Show that in general there is one such anomalous generator, but that if we consider a flavour symmetry amongst only the charged leptons, or only the neutrinos, then there is no QED anomaly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QED ($\lambda_8 + \sqrt{3} \lambda_3$)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_V$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_A$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;QCD and QED&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Note that the two diagonal generators of $SU(3)_V$ are exact symmetries. One of these can be identified with electric charge $Q$. Together with $U(1)_V$ they form the $U(1)^3_V$ symmetry group corresponding to conservation of each quark flavour.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symmetries of the Standard Model I: Overview</title>
      <link>/blog/sm1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/sm1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standard Model is a complicated quantum field theory. Understanding it in detail takes time, but understanding the symmetries of the theory provides a framework with which to understand these details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Symmetries can be classified along many lines. They can be continuous or discrete, global or local, approximate or exact, anomalous, spontaneously broken, and so on. In this series, we will endeavour to discuss each and every symmetry of the Standard Model, and classify them according to each of the categories above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Part I, we will give a schematic overview of the structure of the Standard Model and its gauge symmetries. In Parts II and III we will consider global continuous symmetries, first from the perspective of the low-energy theory, and then from the perspective of the high-energy theory. In Part IV we will consider the discrete symmetries $C$, $P$, and $T$, and in Part V we will collect these results together and discuss how they are affected by some extensions to the theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gauge-symmetries&#34;&gt;Gauge Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting point for the construction of the Standard Model is the gauge group&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \ , $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the first factor represents the colour symmetry of &lt;strong&gt;quantum chromodynamics (QCD)&lt;/strong&gt;, and the second two factors (known as weak isospin and hypercharge) represent the symmetry of the &lt;strong&gt;electroweak&lt;/strong&gt; interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-field-content&#34;&gt;The Field Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Standard Model contains gauge bosons corresponding to each of the gauge groups described above, along with $n_g = 3$ generations of Weyl fermions in the following representations, as well as a single scalar field, the Higgs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$SU(2)_L$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$U(1)_Y$&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Q_L$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 1/6$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$u_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 2/3$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$d_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1/3$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$L_L$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1/2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$e_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = -1$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$\nu_R$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 0$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$\phi$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Trivial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fundamental&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$Y = 1/2$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lagrangian&#34;&gt;The Lagrangian&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most general renormalizable Lagrangian with the above gauge symmetry and field content is the Standard Model. We can group the terms in the Lagrangian into four classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the gauge fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the fermions, including coupling to the gauge fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic terms for the Higgs and Higgs self-interactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yukawa couplings between the fermions and the Higgs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schematically, this Lagrangian is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \begin{align} \mathcal{L} = &amp;amp;-\frac{1}{4} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^{a\mu \nu} \\ &amp;amp;+ \bar{\psi} i  \gamma^\mu D_\mu \psi \\ &amp;amp;+ |D_\mu \phi|^2 - V(\phi) \\ &amp;amp;- Y_d \bar{Q}_L \phi d_R - Y_u \bar{Q}_{L} \phi^c u_R + \mathrm{h.c.} \\ &amp;amp;- Y_e \bar{L}_L \phi e_R - Y_\nu \bar{L}_{L} \phi^c \nu_R + \mathrm{h.c.} \end{align} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an additional class of term one can add to the Lagrangian whose effects are more subtle. These are the theta terms, one for each factor of the gauge group:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathcal{L}_\theta =  \frac{\theta g^2}{64 \pi^2} \epsilon^{\mu \nu \rho \sigma} F^a_{\mu \nu} F^a_{\rho \sigma} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will ignore these terms until Part IV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exact-symmetries&#34;&gt;Exact Symmetries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lagrangian above has many approximate global symmetries which we will discuss in due course. The extent to which these symmetries are approximate is dictated by the various parameters of the theory. For general choices of these parameters (and in reality) the Standard Model has only two exact global continuous symmetries. These are &lt;strong&gt;baryon number&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;lepton number&lt;/strong&gt;. They are not enforced upon the theory &amp;mdash; rather, it is simply not possible to write down renormalizable terms respecting the overall gauge symmetry which violate baryon or lepton number. We sometimes say such symmetries are &lt;strong&gt;accidental&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spontaneous-symmetry-breaking&#34;&gt;Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A symmetry is spontaneously broken if it is respected by the Lagrangian but not by the vacuum of the theory. Spontaneous symmetry breaking is typically caused by fields acquiring a non-zero expectation value in the vacuum. In the Standard Model, there are two sources of spontaneous symmetry breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Higgs field $\phi$ acquires a non-zero VEV. This breaks the gauge symmetry thus:
$$ SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y \to SU(3)_C \times U(1)_Q \ .$$
It also breaks some approximate global symmetries. This is known as &lt;strong&gt;electroweak symmetry breaking&lt;/strong&gt;. The unbroken $U(1)_Q$ symmetry is the symmetry of &lt;strong&gt;quantum electrodynamics (QED)&lt;/strong&gt;. We will discuss this further in Part III.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a lower energy scale, the quark bilinears $\bar{q}q$ acquire a non-zero VEV (equal in magnitude for each flavour). This breaks no further gauge symmetries, but does break some approximate global symmetries. This is known as &lt;strong&gt;chiral symmetry breaking&lt;/strong&gt;. We will discuss this further in Part II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;anomalies&#34;&gt;Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A symmetry is anomalous if it is respected by the Lagrangian but not by the path integral measure. For a symmetry $H$ with generators $t^a$ and a gauge symmetry $G$ with generators $T^a$, we say that $H$ suffers a $G$-anomaly if the &lt;strong&gt;anomaly coefficient&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathrm{tr}(\gamma^5 t^a \{T^b, T^c\}) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is non-zero. In principle it is possible for anomalies to arise from diagrams with three different currents, but this cannot happen in the Standard Model since such diagrams always involve exactly one generator of $SU(2)_L$ or $SU(3)_C$, which is traceless. It is a somewhat magical feature of the Standard Model, which one should check from the table of field representations above, that no gauge symmetry $H$ suffers a $G$-anomaly for any gauge symmetry $G$. Indeed, this is necessary for the theory to be consistent. Nevertheless, there are several global symmetries $H$ which suffer $G$-anomalies, as we shall see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Approximate&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SSB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Anomalous&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(3)_C$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$SU(2)_L \times U(1)_Y$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Down to $U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$U(1)_Q$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Utilities Problem on General Compact Surfaces</title>
      <link>/blog/utilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/utilities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is well known that one cannot connect each of three homes to each of three utilities, without any of the lines of connection crossing, if those lines are restricted to lie in a plane (or equivalently, on the surface of a sphere). Mathematically, we say that the complete bipartite graph $K_{3,3}$ is not planar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible to draw such a graph on the surface of a torus. Indeed, on a torus it is possible to connect each of four homes to each of four utilities, without any lines of connection crossing (an exercise for the curious).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A natural question to ask is: what is the surface of lowest genus $g$ on which it is possible to connect $n$ homes to $n$ utilities, without crossings?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-lower-bound&#34;&gt;A Lower Bound&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a lower bound on the genus required. Suppose the complete bipartite graph $K_{n,n}$ can be drawn without crossings on the genus-$g$ surface. Let $e = n^2$ denote the number of edges in the graph, $f$ the number of faces, and let $\chi = 2 - 2g$ denote the Euler characteristic of the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shortest cycle in $K_{n,n}$ has length four. Thus each face of the graph must have at least four sides, and since each side is shared by two faces, we must have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 2 e \geq 4 f  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By definition, we have $2n - e + f = \chi$. Thus we can write the above inequality as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \frac{e}{2} \leq 2n - \chi = 2(n + g - 1) \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we find that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ g \geq \frac{(n-2)^2}{4} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-upper-bound&#34;&gt;An Upper Bound&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that any finite graph can be drawn without crossings on a surface with sufficiently large genus. Roughly speaking, we can simply send each edge through its own handle, and so $g \leq e(G)$ gives a simple upper bound on the genus required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve this bound, first consider the case that $n = 2m$ is even. By considering the houses in pairs, and likewise for the utilities, our task is to connect each house pair to each utility pair with a copy of $K_{2,2}$, of which there will be $m^2$ in total. Note that we can represent a $K_{2,2}$ passing through a handle like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;pics/k22.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we can clearly draw our graph with $m^2$ handles like so ($m = 2$):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;pics/simple.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here black dots indicate houses and white dots indicate utilities. This gives a simple upper bound (for $n$ odd or even) on the genus of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$g \leq \lceil n/2 \rceil^2 \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-better-upper-bound&#34;&gt;A Better Upper Bound&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us pair the houses and utilities as before. We can easily draw $m$ copies of $K_{2,2}$ on the plane like so ($m=3$):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;pics/bound1.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we can add $m-1$ further copies of $K_{2,2}$ without difficulty:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;pics/bound2.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now claim that we can add the remaining $(m-1)^2$ copies of $K_{2,2}$ using $(m-1)^2$ handles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;pics/bound3.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our minimum required genus is hence bounded above by $g \leq (m-1)^2 = (n-2)^2/4$. But this is precisely the lower bound on the genus we previously found!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For $n$ odd I have not found so neat a solution. It seems clear that the genus required should be smaller than that for $K_{n+1,n+1}$, yet it may not be possible to achieve the lower bound described above (for one thing, it is impossible for every face to have four sides, since the number of edges is odd). More thought is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-partial-solution&#34;&gt;A Partial Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have found that when $n$ is even, the minimum genus required to draw $K_{n,n}$ without crossings is
$$ g = \frac{(n-2)^2}{4} \ . $$
Whilst for $n$ odd, we have found that this minimum genus lies in the range
$$ (n/2 - 1)^2 \leq g \leq (\lceil n/2 \rceil - 1)^2 \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides pinning down the case of odd $n$ precisely, a natural next question to ask is how this result extends to the graphs $K_{m,n}$ for $m \neq n$.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longest Increasing Subsequence</title>
      <link>/blog/subsequence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/subsequence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a finite sequence $(a_1, a_2, \ldots, a_k)$ of real numbers, how can one find the longest subsequence satisfying $a_{n(i+1)} &amp;gt; a_{n(i)}$ for all $i$? A sequence of length $k$ has $2^k$ subsequences and checking each case may not be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-solution&#34;&gt;A Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose our sequence begins $(1,10,11,12,2,3,\ldots)$. If we begin our subsequence with $a_1 = 1$, we are left with the decision whether to next take $a_2 = 10$, thus committing to the exclusion of $a_5$ and $a_6$, or whether perhaps to skip the second to fourth elements in the hope of finding more elements less than $a_2$ further down the line. Which decision is better could depend on elements all the way to the end of the sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, one is tempted to start thinking from the other end. Suppose we begin with $a_k$. Clearly there is nowhere else to go, and our longest subsequence will have length one. Now suppose we begin with $a_{k-1}$. We have hardly more choice in this case: we include $a_k$ if it is greater than $a_{k-1}$, and not otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now suppose we begin with $a_{k-2}$. We have already determined the longest subsequence beginning with $a_i$ for each $i &amp;gt; k-2$. Thus, we need only check which such $a_i$ satisfy $a_i &amp;gt; a_{k-2}$, and of those, prepend $a_{k-2}$ to the longest corresponding subsequence. This will generate the longest subsequence beginning with $a_{k-2}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s clear we can continue this process, tracking backwards through the sequence to determine the longest ascending subsequence beginning with each element, and once this is complete we can choose the longest among them as our solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-implementation&#34;&gt;An Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to implement this idea uses Python dictionaries:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;a = [1,10,11,12,2,3,4,13,14,15,5,6,7,8]
k = len(a)

# prepend a small number a_0 so that the longest subsequence necessarily begins with a_0
a = [min(a)-1] + a
# create a dictionary of the longest subsequences starting from a_i
longsubseq = {k : [a[-1]]}

for i in reversed(range(k)):
    # restrict the dictionary to those j with a_j &amp;gt; a_i
    lss = {j: longsubseq[j] for j in range(i, k+1) if a[j] &amp;gt; a[i]}
    # from these choose m such that a_m begins the longest subsequence
    m = max(lss, key = lambda j: len(lss[j]), default = 0)
    # append this subsequence to a_i
    if m == 0: subseq = [a[i]]
    else: subseq = [a[i]] + longsubseq[m]
    longsubseq[i] = subseq

solution = longsubseq[0][1:] 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know that Python dictionaries are necessarily the fastest way to implement this idea, but they are conceptually clean at least.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
