<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geometry | George Johnson</title>
    <link>/category/geometry/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/geometry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Geometry</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu7bc565721a69e427bf94bf1315c635aa_13529_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Geometry</title>
      <link>/category/geometry/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Irrotational Vector Fields Conservative? An Excursion into Algebraic Topology</title>
      <link>/blog/derham/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/derham/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;conservative-and-irrotational-vector-fields&#34;&gt;Conservative and Irrotational Vector Fields&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smooth vector field $\mathbf{F}$ in $\mathbb{R}^3$ is known as &lt;strong&gt;conservative&lt;/strong&gt; if it can be written as the gradient of a scalar field: $\mathbf{F} = \nabla f$. A vector field is termed &lt;strong&gt;irrotational&lt;/strong&gt; if it has zero curl: $\nabla \times \mathbf{F} = \mathbf{0}$. It is not hard to check that all conservative vector fields are irrotational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The converse also happens to be true:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theorem 1:&lt;/em&gt; an irrotational vector field on $\mathbb{R}^3$ is conservative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One consequence of this is that the line integral of an irrotational field between any two points is independent of the path taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-exception&#34;&gt;An Exception&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In electromagnetism, the magnetic field around a static current-carrying wire obeys Ampère&amp;rsquo;s Law: $\nabla \times \mathbf{B} = \mathbf{0}$. We may thus write the magnetic field in terms of a so-called magnetic scalar potential, $\mathbf{B} = \nabla \psi$. However, it is clear from the circulating nature of the solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathbf{B}= ? $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that the integral of $\mathbf{B}$ along a circle around the wire is non-zero. In fact the magnetic scalar potential does not exist everywhere. This apparent conflict with the above statements can be resolved in two ways: either we note that $\mathbf{B}$ fails to be irrotational inside the wire, where it obeys the equation $\nabla \times \mathbf{B} = \mu_0 \mathbf{J}$; or we don&amp;rsquo;t consider the wire to be part of our space, and treat our field as defined not on all of $\mathbb{R}^3$ (as required for the theorem to hold), but on $\mathbb{R}^3 - \mathrm{line}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking this latter viewpoint, an interesting question poses itself: what features of a space permit or prevent us from expressing irrotational vector fields as the gradient of a scalar field? What differs between $M = \mathbb{R}^3 - \mathrm{line}$ and $\mathbb{R}^3$? The answer to this question lies in the domain of topology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;de-rhams-theorem&#34;&gt;De Rham&amp;rsquo;s Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a space $M$, the &lt;strong&gt;first de Rham cohomology group&lt;/strong&gt; $H^1(M)$ measures the extent to which this cannot be done. What is meant by extent? Say something about equivalence classes. Thus $H^1(M) = \mathbb{R}$ and $H^1(\mathbb{R}^3) = 0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crucial result of this subject is de Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem, which states that the de Rham cohomology groups are isomorphic to the homology groups of the space:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ H^r(M) \cong H_r(M) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The homology groups of a space describe its topology. In particular, they are invariant under homotopy equivalence (continuous deformations of the space).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;real-or-integer-homology&#34;&gt;Real or Integer Homology?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talk above of homology groups with real coefficients, though homology groups of spaces are typically treated with integer coefficients, rather than the real coefficients as in de Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the space $\mathbb{R}P^2 \times \mathbb{R}$. This is homotopy equivalent to $\mathbb{R}P^2$ and hence has first homology group $H_1 = \mathbb{Z}_2$. Thus, in terms of real homology&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;homology-or-homotopy&#34;&gt;Homology or Homotopy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is sometimes said that irrotational vector fields are conservative when the domain of the field is &lt;strong&gt;simply connected&lt;/strong&gt;. To be simply connected is to have trivial first &lt;strong&gt;homotopy group&lt;/strong&gt;, $\pi_1$. Like the first homology group, the first homotopy group measures codimension-one holes in our space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the first homology and first homotopy groups are in general different. The relation between them is given by the Hurewicz theorem, which states that the first homology group is the abelianisation of the first homotopy group &amp;mdash; that is, the quotient of $\pi_1$ under the equivalence relation $xy \sim yx$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, if our space is simply connected, then it also has trivial first homology group, and irrotational vector fields are conservative, as is claimed. However, the above discussion shows that simple connectedness isn&amp;rsquo;t a necessary condition for this. Indeed, any space with a fundamental group which has trivial abelianisation will have this property. Such groups as known as &lt;strong&gt;perfect groups&lt;/strong&gt;, and are in some sense maximally non-abelian. The smallest non-trivial example is the alternating group $A_5$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the simplest example of a space with perfect non-trivial fundamental group is the &lt;strong&gt;Poincaré homology sphere&lt;/strong&gt;. This is obtained as the quotient of $SO(3)$ by the icosahedral group $I \cong A_5$, the rotational symmetries of the icosahedron. This space can hence be thought of as the space of all geometrically distinguishable orientations of the icosahedron. Passing to the double cover of $SO(3)$, we can also write this as the quotient $S^3 / 2I$, where $2I$ is the binary icosahedral group (the preimage of $I$ under the covering map from $S^3$ to $SO(3)$). The fundamental group of this space is $2I$, which is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, a simpler example would be simply $\mathb{R}P^2 \times \mathbb{R}$ as in the previous section. Here the first homology and first homotopy groups are equal and non-trivial, but the first de Rham cohomology is nevertheless trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;generalising-to-two-dimensions&#34;&gt;Generalising to Two Dimensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That all these groups are termed the &amp;lsquo;first&amp;rsquo; of their kind suggests that higher homology and cohomology groups exist. Indeed they do, and de Rham&amp;rsquo;s theorem states that the $n^\mathrm{th}$ homology and $n^\mathrm{th}$ cohomology groups of a space are isomorphic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By way of example, the second de Rham cohomology group measures the extent to which a &lt;strong&gt;solenoidal vector field&lt;/strong&gt; (one with zero divergence) can be written as the curl of another vector field. The second homology group measures the number of codimension-two holes in the space. Thus $\mathbb{R}^3$ with a point removed has $H_1 = \mathbb{R}$. The magnetic field around a magnetic monopole, which can be considered a field on this space, &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be written as the curl of a magnetic vector potential. This fact leads to the story about charge quantization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no simple relation between higher homology and homotopy groups (although the Hurewicz theorem provides a partial answer in this direction). Thus, one should not make the mistake of resorting to the second homotopy group to determine whether a vector potential exists. Two counterexamples to this end are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The space $T^2 \times \mathbb{R}$, where $T^2$ is the 2-torus, has $H_2 = \mathbb{Z}$ but $\pi_2 = 0$. Despite having trivial second homotopy group, there exist solenoidal vector fields which cannot be written as the curl of another vector field. The simplest example would be $\mathbf{B} = \mathbf{e}_3$, corresponding to a constant vector field pointing along the $\mathbb{R}$ direction. Integrating this field over the torus at some fixed $z \in \mathbb{R}$ gives a positive number, yet the integral of any curl over such surface must be zero by Stokes&#39; theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The space $\mathbb{R}P^2 \times \mathbb{R}$ has $H_2 = 0$ but $\pi_2 = \mathbb{Z}$. Thus all solenoidal vector fields on this space can be written as the curl of another vector field, despite the non-trivial second homotopy group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-words&#34;&gt;Final Words&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story above generalises to other dimensions. The curl is replaced by the more general operator the &lt;strong&gt;exterior derivative&lt;/strong&gt;. The cohomology groups of a given space capture the extent to which certain objects can be expressed as the exterior derivative of others. The theorem of de Rham applies as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else should I say?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Euler&#39;s Polyhedron Formula and the Gauss-Bonnet Theorem</title>
      <link>/blog/polyhedron/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/polyhedron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;eulers-polyhedron-formula&#34;&gt;Euler&amp;rsquo;s Polyhedron Formula&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a wonderful theorem due to Euler (1752) which states that for a convex polyhedron with $V$ vertices, $E$ edges, and $F$ faces:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V - E + F = 2 \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post we will sketch a proof of this result, and then extend it to non-convex polyhedra. Our starting point will be a result in the subject of spherical geometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-angle-defect-formula&#34;&gt;The Angle Defect Formula&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a triangle drawn on the plane, the sum of the interior angles is $\pi$. For a triangle drawn on the surface of a unit sphere, whose sides are arcs of great circles, the internal angles $\alpha,\beta,\gamma$ satisfy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi = \text{area of triangle} \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prove this, consider extending the sides of the triangle into three great circles. These divide the sphere into eight regions. By the symmetry of the figure under the exchange of antipodal points, our triangle and the three faces which neighbour it constitute exactly half the area of the sphere. The total area of these four regions is hence $2 \pi$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now our triangle together with any one of the three neighbouring regions form the surface of a spherical wedge. A wedge of angle $\theta$ has surface area $2 \theta$ (this gives an area $4 \pi$ when $\theta = 2 \pi$). If we consider the three possible wedges in turn, their total area is hence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 2(\alpha + \beta + \gamma) \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this total area can be written as the sum of the areas of those regions neighbouring our triangle, plus thrice the area of the triangle. Since we know that the four regions together have an area of $2 \pi$, we can rearrange for the area of our triangle, giving the angle defect formula quoted above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-euler&#34;&gt;Back to Euler&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the angle defect formula to hand, we can embark on our proof of Euler&amp;rsquo;s formula. Given any convex polyhedron, choose a point in its interior as the origin and form the projection onto the surface of the unit sphere. Deform the edges so that they form the arcs of great circles (that this is always possible is plausible, though we will not prove it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any face with four or more vertices, consider inserting a new edge. This adds precisely one face and one edge, and hence leaves unchanged the quantity $\chi = V - E + F$. We can hence, without loss of generality, take our polyhedron to be constructed from triangular faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For such a polyhedron, each face has three edges, and each edge is shared by two faces. Thus we can relate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ E = \frac{3}{2} F  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each triangular face, we can apply the angle defect formula. Summing over all faces, we find&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sum_F (\alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi) = \text{area of sphere} = 4 \pi  \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sum over all faces of all internal angles of each face can be reorganised as a sum over all vertices of all angles at each vertex. But the angles at a vertex sum to $2 \pi$, and hence the above formula reads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 2 \pi V - \pi F = 4 \pi \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the results above can be combined to give Euler&amp;rsquo;s formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V - E + F = 2  \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;generalising-the-angle-defect-formula&#34;&gt;Generalising the Angle Defect Formula&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those familiar with Riemannian geometry, the notion of an angle defect may appear connected with the notion of parallel transport. Indeed, the failure of a vector to return to itself upon parallel transport around some small rectangle seems to correspond to the failure of the interior angles to sum to $2 \pi$. But this failure can also be quantified by the Riemann tensor, a measure of the curvature of the space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may thus hope to generalise the angle defect formula to arbitrary curved surfaces thus. Let $K$ be an appropriate scalar curvature, which takes the value $1$ for the unit sphere. Let $\alpha,\beta,\gamma$ be the internal angles of a triangle $\triangle$ on this surface, whose edges are geodesics. Then we postulate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi = \int_{\triangle} K \ \mathrm{d}A \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This formula turns out to be true &amp;mdash; it is called the local Gauss-Bonnet theorem, and holds with $K$ the Gauss curvature of the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-gauss-bonnet-theorem&#34;&gt;The Gauss-Bonnet Theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this new formula to hand, we can repeat the previous steps for any polyhedron, not necessarily a convex one. First map the polyhedron to some smooth surface, topologically equivalent to it. Deform the edges so that they are geodesics on this surface, and insert new edges so that all faces are triangular. We then have $E = 3F/2$ as before, but now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sum_F (\alpha + \beta + \gamma - \pi) = \int K \ \mathrm{d}A \ .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reorganising the sum over faces as a sum over vertices, this gives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ 2 \pi V - \pi F = \int K \ \mathrm{d}A  \ , $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and altogether we have the global Gauss-Bonnet theorem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V - E + F = \frac{1}{2 \pi} \int K \ \mathrm{d}A  \ . $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;musings&#34;&gt;Musings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At once this theorem tells us two pretty facts about polyhedra and curved surfaces. Firstly, it implies that for any two polyhedra which are topologically equivalent, the quantity $\chi = V - E + F$ &amp;mdash; known as the Euler characteristic &amp;mdash; must take the same value, since both can be mapped to the same surface with fixed integrated curvature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it implies that for any two smooth surfaces which are topologically equivalent, the integrated curvature must take the same value, since both surfaces can be triangulated with the same polyhedron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Said more succinctly, the integrated curvature and the Euler characteristic are both &lt;strong&gt;topological invariants&lt;/strong&gt; of closed surfaces, equal to one another by the Gauss-Bonnet theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
